<?xml version="1.0"?>
  <ftAccount id="08">
    <bibInfo medium="letter" distance="primary" text="copy">
			<pubArticle>
        No. 83.&#8212;To Major Genl. Knox, Secy. of War
      </pubArticle>
      <pubAuthor id="">
        Major General Anthony Wayne
      </pubAuthor>
      <pubTitle>
        Anthony Wayne Letter Books: October 23, 1793-September 20, 1794
      </pubTitle>
      <pubCollection>
        Anthony Wayne Family Papers, Clements Library
      </pubCollection>
      <pubVol>
        32
      </pubVol>
      <pubName>
        Wayne Family; University of Michigan
      </pubName>
		</bibInfo>
		<account>
			<header>
				Head Quarters
				Grand Glaize 28th Augt. 1794.
			</header>
			<opening>
				Sir,
			</opening>
			<para>
				It's with infinite pleasure that
        I now announce to you the brilliant success
        of the Federal Army under my command in
        a general Action with the combined force of the
        hostile Indians &amp; a considerable number of
        the Voluntiers &amp; Militia of Detroit on the
        20th. instant on the banks of the Miamis, in
        the vicinity of the British Post &amp; Garrison
        at the foot of the rapids.
			</para>
			<para>
				The army advanced from this
        place on the 15th instant and arrived at
        Roche de bout on the 18th.; the 19th. we were
        employed in making a temporary post for
        the reception of our stores &amp; baggage &amp; in
        reconnoitering the position of the enemy, who
        were encamped behind a thick brushy-wood
        and the British Fort.
			</para>
			<para>
				At 8. o'clock on the morning of the
        20. the Army again advanced in columns
        agreeably to the standing order of march:
        the Legion on the right Flank covered by
        the Miamis, one Brigade of mounted Voluntiers
        on the left under Brigadier General
        Todd, and the other in the rear under Brigadr
        General Barbee: a select battalion of mounted
        voluntiers moved in front of the Legion, commanded
        by Major Price, who was directed
        to keep sufficiently advanced&#8212;so as to give
        timely notice for the troops in case of action.;
			</para>
			<para>
				It being yet undetermined whether the
        Indians wou'd decide on peace or war.
      </para>
			<para>
				After advancing about five miles, Major Price's
        corps received so severe a fire from the enemy, who
        were secreted in the woods &amp; high grass, as to
        compel them to retreat.&#8212;
			</para>
			<para>
				The Legion was immediately formed
        in two lines, principally in a close thick wood
        which extended for miles on our left; and
        for very considerable distance in front, the
        ground being cover'd with old fallen timber
        probably occasioned by a tornado, which
        rendered it impracticable for the Cavalry
        to act with effect, &amp; afforded the enemy the
        most favorable covert for their savage mode
        of warfare: they were formed in three lines
        within supporting distance of each other, &amp;
        extending near two miles at right angles
        with the river.&#8212;
      </para>
      <para>
        I soon discovered from the weight
        of the fire, &amp; extent of their lines that the
        enemy were in full force in front in possession
        of their favorite ground &amp; endeavoring to turn
        our left flank, I therefore gave orders,
        for the second line to advance to support
        the first, &amp; directed Major General Scott to
        gain &amp; turn the right flank of the savages,
        with the whole of the mounted Voluntiers
        by a circuitous route: at the same time I ordered
        the front line to advance &amp; charge with trailed
        arms, &amp; rouse the Indians from their
        coverts at the point of the bayonet, &amp; when up,
        to deliver a close &#8212; well directed fire on their
        backs followed by a brisk charge&#8212;so as not
        to give time to load again:&#8212;I also ordered
        Capt Mis Campbell who commanded the Legionary
        Cavalry to turn the left flank of the enemy
        next the river, and which afforded a favorable
        field for that corps to act in.&#8212;
			</para>
			<para>
				All those orders were obeyed with
        spirit &amp; promptitude&#8212;but such was the impetuosity
        of the charge by the first line of
        Infantry, that the Indians &amp; Canadian
        militia &amp; voluntiers were drove from all their
        coverts in so short a time, that although
        every possible exertion was used by the Officers of
        the second line of the Legion, &amp; by Generals
        Scott, Todd &amp; Barbee of the mounted voluntiers
        to gain their proper positions, but
        part of each could get up in season to participate
        in the action; the enemy being drove
        in the course of one hour more than two
        miles thro' the thick woods already mentioned,
        by less than one half their numbers.&#8212;
      </para>
      <para>
        From every account the enemy amounted
        to two thousand combatants: the troops actually
        engaged against them were short of nine-hundred.&#8212;this
        horde of savages with their
        allies abandoned themselves to flight, and
        dispersed with terror &amp; dismay; leaving our
        victorious Army in full &amp; quiet possession of
        the field of battle, which terminated under
        the influence of the guns of the British Garrison
        as you will observe by the enclosed correspondence
        between Major Campbell the Commandant
        &amp; myself upon the occasion.&#8212;
			</para>
			<para>
				The bravery &amp; conduct of every
        Officer belonging to the Army from the Generals
        down to the Ensigns merits my highest
        approbation.&#8212;there were however some, whose
        rank &amp; situation placed their conduct in a
        very conspicuous point of view, and which I
        observed with pleasure &amp; the most lively
        gratitude: among whom I must beg leave
        to mention Brigr. Genl. Wilkinson and Colo.
        Hamtramck, the commandants of the right
        &amp; left wings of the Legion, whose brave example
        inspired the troops; to them I must add the
        names of my faithful &amp; gallant Aids de Camp
        Captain's De Butts &amp; T. Lewis &amp; Lieut. Harrison
        who, with the Adjt. General Major Mills rendered
        the most essential services by communicating
        my orders in every direction, &amp; by their
        conduct &amp; bravery, exciting the troops to
        press for victory.&#8212;Lieut. Covington upon
        whom the Command of the Cavalry now
        devolved, cut down two savages with his
        own hand &amp; Lieut. Webb one, in turning
        the enemy's left flank.&#8212;
			</para>
			<para>
				The wounds received by Capts.
        Slough &amp; Prior &amp; Lieut Campbell Smith
        (an extra aid de Camp to Genl Wilkinson) of
        the Legionary Infantry, &amp; Capt. Van Ransselaer
        of the Dragoons, &amp; Capt. Rawlins,
        Lieut McKenney &amp; Ensign Duncan of the
        mounted Voluntiers bear honorable
        testimony of their bravery &amp; conduct.&#8212;
			</para>
			<para>
				Captains H. Lewis &amp; Brock with their
        companies of light Infantry had to sustain
        an unequal fire for some time, which they
        supported with fortitude.&#8212;In fact every
        officer &amp; soldier who had an opportunity to
        come into Action displayed that true bravery
        which will always insure success.&#8212;
      <para>
      </para>
        And here permit me to declare,
        that I never discovered more true spirit
        and anxiety for action than appeared to pervade
        the whole of the mounted voluntiers; &amp; I am
        well persuaded that had the enemy mantained
        their favorite ground but for one half hour
        longer, they would have most severely felt
        the prowess of that corps.&#8212;
			</para>
			<para>
				but, whilst I pay this just tribute
        to the living, I must not forget the gallant
        dead: among whom we have to lament the
        early death of those worthy &amp; brave Officers
        Capt. Miss Campbell of the Dragoons and
        Lieut. Towles of the light Infantry of the
        Legion who fell in the first charge.&#8212;
			</para>
			<para>
				Enclosed is a particular return of
        the killed &amp; wounded&#8212;the loss of the Enemy
        was more than double, that of the Federal
        Army&#8212;the woods were strewed for a considerable
        distance with the dead bodies of
        Indians &amp;their white auxiliaries, the
        latter, armed with British muskets and
        bayonets.&#8212;
			</para>
			<para>
				We remained three days &amp; nights
        on the banks of the Miamis in front of the
        field of battle, during which time all the
        houses &amp; corn fields were consumed &amp; destroyed
        for a considerable distance both above and
        below Fort Miamis, as well as within pistol
        shot of that Garrison, who were compelled
        to remain tacit spectators of this general devestation
        &amp; conflagration.&#8212;among which were the
        houses, stores &amp; property of Colo. McKee the British
        Indian Agent &amp; principal stimulator of the
        war now existing between the United States
        and the savages.&#8212;
			</para>
			<para>
				The Army returned to this place
        on the 27. by easy marches, laying waste the
        villages &amp; cornfields for about fifty miles
        on each side of the Miamis: there remains
        yet a number of villages &amp; a great quantity
        of corn to be consumed or destroyed upon
        Au Glaize &amp; the Miamis above this place,
        which will be effected in the course of a
        few days.&#8212;in the interim we shall improve
        Fort Defiance, &amp; as soon as the escort returns
        with the necessary supplies from Greeneville
        &amp; Fort Recovery, the Army will proceed to
        the Miami villages in order to accomplish
        the object of the Campaign.&#8212;
			</para>
			<para>
				It is however not improbable
        that the enemy may make one more desperate
        effort against the Army; as it is said that a
        reenforcement was hourly expected at Fort
        Miamis from Niagara, as well as numerous
        tribes of Indians living on the margins
        &amp; Islands of the Lakes: this is a business
        rather to be wished for than dreaded, whilst
        the Army remains in force&#8212;their numbers
        will only tend to confuse the savages, and the
        victory will be the more complete and
        decisive,&#8212;and which may eventually ensure
        a permanent &amp; happy peace.
			</para>
			<closing>
				Under these Impressions, I have
        the honor to be

        your most obedt.
        &amp; very huml. Sert.

				Anty. Wayne
			</closing>
			<addressee>
				The Honble.
				Maj. Gen. Knox
				Secy. of War.
			</addressee>
      <postscript>
        NB. I had forgot to mention that I met my
        Flag on the 16., who was returning with an
        evasive answer in order to gain time
        for the arrival of the reenforcement mentioned
        by the Shawanoe Indians, &amp; which actually
        did arrive two days before the action.
      </postscript>
		</account>
  </ftAccount>