<?xml version="1.0"?>
  <ftAccount id="07">
    <bibInfo medium="journal_article" distance="primary" text="edited_reprint">
      <pubArticle>
        A Journal of a Campaign in the Year 1794 Under the Command of Major General Charles Scott
      </pubArticle>
      <pubAuthor persID="">
        Anonymous
      </pubAuthor>
      <pubEditor persID="KNOPF">
        Richard C. Knopf
      </pubEditor>
      <pubTitle>
        Two Journals of the Kentucky Volunteers 1793 and 1794
      </pubTitle>
      <pubName>
        The Filson Club Historical Quarterly
      </pubName>
      <pubVol>
        27
      </pubVol>
      <pubIss>
        3
      </pubIss>
      <pubDate date="1953">
        1953
      </pubYear>
      <pubPage>
        258-273;279-281
      </pubPage>
		</bibInfo>
		<account>
			<header>
				Wednesday 20
			</header>
        <para>
          Clear, The Baggage being Deposited, in the Fortification the
          Army moved at 6 in the following order Capt Baker &amp; Capt
          Arnold's Companies under the Comd. of Majr. Price formd. the Front
          or Corps of observation. Brigd. Genl. Todd on the Left Genl.
          Wilkinson on the Margin of the River the artillery and bagage in
          the Centre Genl Barbee in the rear the Ground for 5 miles high
          &amp; dry open Woods tall large Oaks at 45 Minutes past 8 the
          Front was attactd. by a number of Indians in the high Grass They
          returnd. the fire and fell back to the Front of the Federal Army, which
          likewise fell back untill They Formed the line of Battle when they
          movd. on driving the Enemy before them the Cavelry chargd. here
          with the loss of the brave Capt. M. Campbell at this Time Genl
          Todd Brigade was forming a line and immediately got into action
          after getting orders from Genl. Scott to dismount and move
          forwards in a lo swampy ground with a great dale of
          fallen Timber and thick brush with Hoop and black Ash bushes which
          rendred the place difficult to see a Man 10 yds the action Continud
          all together 1 hour &amp; 20 Minutes with the Volunteers half an hour
          when the Indians and their white allies part British and some French
          retired in a very precipitate manner eaving their dead and some of
          their wounded on the Field we moved back over the ground
          collectd. the wounded and moved to the Federal troops where they
          were haltd and had the wound dressd. and litters made to carry
          them in, the Army then movd. forwarward within sight of the
          British Garison where the Army incampd on a high Bank in a thick 
          Brush. the Action was General and conducted with propriety and
          honour to the American Arms and Their Officer in sight of the
          army was the River divided by a large Island well Cultivated with
          Corn &amp; beans and a number of Stacks of Hay which was a pleaseing
          sight to the Army but more particularly to the Volunteers that was
          across the River and bringing loads of Corn and Hay in one hour
          after the army got to the ground under the Guns of the British
          Garison a smart Shower of Rain after the action.
				</para>
			</account>
  </ftAccount>