<?xml version="1.0"?>
  <ftAccount id="12">
    <bibInfo medium="broadside" distance="secondary" text="original">
      <pubTitle>
        BALTIMORE, September 27. By two gentlemen just arrived from Kentucky we have been favored with the following very Important Intelligence. LEXINGTON, September 8, 1794. An express arrived here on Saturday evening about 8 o'clock with letters from the army, from which we have collected the following particulars:
      </pubTitle>
      <pubName>
        Yundt and Patton, near the court-house
      </pubName>
      <pubDate date="1794-09-27"></pubDate>
      <pubPlace city="Baltimore" state="Maryland"></pubPlace>
    </bibInfo>
    <account>
      <para>
        On the 20th ult. about 146 miles advanced
        of Greenville, the advance
        guard, consisting of two companies, were
        attacked by about 1100 Indians and Canadian
        milita; the attack being sudden and
        unexpected, the advance guard fell back on
        the main army and threw them into confusion,
        which occasioned a retreat of about one
        hundred paces before they were ordered to
        charge the enemy, which was instantly done;
        upon which the enemy immediately gave
        ground, and our men rushing forward with
        such impetuosity, the enemy were dislodged
        from their coverts, and the cavalry taking
        advantage of that event, pursued them about
        two miles, when they dispersed. The action
        continued about an hour and a quarter;
        we had about 30 men killed, and 80 wounded;
        among the former are captain Campbell
        of the cavalry, and lieutenant Towles of the
        infantry. Among the latter are captain
        Slough, capt. Vanransallear, capt. Prior and
        lieut. Campbell Smith, of the federal army;&#8212;Seven
        of the Volunteers were killed, and
        fourteen wounded. 127 scalps were taken,
        and a number killed in the river that were
        not scalped. The army remained three days
        on the ground, and returned to Fort-Defiance,
        at the mouth of the Auglaize, where
        they were on the 24th ult.
      </para>
      <para>
        The action happened within sight of a
        strong British fort, regularly built, and garrisoned
        with three hundred men, between
        forty and fifty miles below Fort-Defiance, on
        the Maumee of the Lakes. The commander
        in chief sent a flag to major Campbell, commander
        of the British garrison, to march his
        men out to the nearest British post, and give
        up the fort, both of which he positively refused.
        The Indians had 5000 acres of land
        in corn, all in excellent order on the bottoms
        of the Maumee river, a considerable quantity
        of which the army have destroyed.
      </para>
      <para>
        The following list of the names of the killed and
        wounded of the Kentucky volunteers, was
        received this day.
      </para>
      <para>
        KILLED. John Jackson, Alexander Innes,
        William Mitchell, Thomas Moore, William
        Steel, Benjamin Bell, and James Wiley.
      </para>
      <para>
        WOUNDED. Captain Rawlings, lieutenant
        M'Kinney, ensign Duncan. Privates, George
        M'Cullock, John Howard, Robert
        Scott, John Hinkston, Isaac Rankins, James
        Cost, James Stewart, Benjamin Bantle, John
        Montgomery, and William Woodrow.
      </para>
      <closing>
        BALTIMORE: Printed by Yundt and Patton, near the Court-House.
      </closing>
    </account>
  </ftAccount>
