<?xml version="1.0"?>
  <ftAccount id="11">
    <bibInfo medium="letter" distance="primary" text="edited_reprint">
      <pubArticle>
        From William Campbell to R.G. England
      </pubArticle>
      <pubAuthor id="">
        Major William Campbell
      </pubAuthor>
      <pubEditor id="">
        Brigadier General E. A. Cruikshank, LL.D., F.R.S.C.
      </pubEditor>
      <pubTitle>
        The Correspondence of Lieut. Governor John Graves Simcoe, with Allied Documents relating to his Administration of the Government of Upper Canada
      </pubTitle>
      <pubVol>
        2
      </pubVol>
      <pubName>
        Ontario Historical Society
      </pubName>
      <pubDate date="1924"></pubDate>
      <pubPlace city="Toronto" state="Ontario" country="Canada"></pubPlace>
      <pubPage>398-399</pubPage>
    </bibInfo>
    <account>
        <header>
          Fort Miamis, 21st August 1794.
        </header>
        <opening>
          Sir,
        </opening>
        <para>
          I sent last night a dispatch to you, to be forwarded by Colonel McKee wherever
          he should be found, somewhere lower down this River.&#8212;In it I detailed the transactions
          of the day&#8212;the chief purpose of which was to inform you, that the Americans
          and Indians had had an engagement, and the latter were beat, and had retired
          below this Post, how far I do not know&#8212;
        </para>
        <para>
          From the circumstance of an American Army having taken Post on the heights
          opposite to Colonel McKee's, Almost within reach of the Guns of this Fort, and
          remained there upwards of twenty-four hours, without any explanation on their
          part, I conceived it a duty I owed to my station, and indispensably necessary in
          support of the honor of the British Colours to desire to be informed upon what
          terms they Approached so near this Post. I refer you to my letter to Him, now
          enclosed (and which I hope you will not think unguarded) together with his
          Answer. I sent my Flag by Captain Spears at Eleven o'Clock this Morning.
          Captain Spears was stopped at their out Post, and was desired to return immediately,
          as the Woods were full of Riffle Men, and they were Affraid of his Safety,
          from Accident. But that an Answer should be sent presently. It arrived at Four
          o'Clock. It appears to me, a vain production and still leaves me a cautious
          part to Act. At the same time, if Any of his Troops wantonly Insults this Post,
          it shall not be with impunity.
        </para>
        <para>
          I sincerely hope the Governor himself may soon arrive, and take all responsibility
          upon him.
        </para>
        <para>
          I trust a Reinforcement from you is not far off at present, I conceive there is
          no danger in coming up this River, how long it may be so, is impossible for me to
          say, at the particular request of Mr. Pilkington and Mr. Adye, I keep Captain
          Harrow and his Sailors&#8212;I had determined otherwise just now, knowing that you
          may have great occasion for him, but their entreaties have prevailed.
        </para>
        <para>
          We have not seen or heard a word about a Savage all day&#8212;It has been a matter
          of great comfort to me, that the Battle of Yesterday terminated without bringing
          me into a scrape, but surely my situation is a very extraordinary one, hundreds
          of the American Cavalry are constantly skirting the Wood all around us, and at
          this Moment, A number of their Officers are looking at us from the Point of Colonel
          McKee's Island. You have also enclosed the Information of a Deserter who came
          in last Night. You will observe he mentions Lascell as being taken Prisoner, but
          here, we all think he Deserted.
        </para>
        <para>
          Drumer Bevan deserted from us this morning about Eight o'Clock, He went
          down to the River to wash his shirts and crept through the Abatis at the Water
          Side.
        </para>
        <closing>
          I have the Honor to be, Sir, &amp;c., &amp;c.,
          Wm. Campbell.
        </closing>
        <addressee>
          Lieut. Col. England, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.
        </addressee>
        <source>
          A Copy.
          Rd. England.
          J. G. S.
          Endorsed:&#8212;Copy of a Letter from Major Wm. Campbell to Lieut.-Colonel England.
          Dated Augt. 21st 1794
          Received Augt. 23rd 1794
          In Lt.-Gov. Simcoe's No. 34 30th Augt. 1794.
        </source>
      </account>