<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE battle_accounts SYSTEM "battle_accounts.dtd">

<battle_accounts>
	<battle_account id="underwood" medium="journal">
		<source type="book" edited="yes" secondary="yes">
			<title></title>
			<author></author>
			<pubdate></pubdate>
			<
		</source>
		<text>
			<place>Camp Deposite</place>, the <date>20th August 1794</date>--

			This <time>morning</time> the army was under arms, <time>at day light</time> and our
			<action side="american" unit="all">line of march arranged</action>. <person>Lietenant Hary Beverly Towles</person> was
			detailed to take command of the front guard, he <action side="american" unit="front_guard">was ordered to
			march on in front</action>, <action side="american" unit="columns">the main army commenced there march</action>,
			<person>General Charles Scott</person> with his mounted Volunteers were placed
			in the rear. After marching 3 or 4 miles the front guard was
			fired on, &amp; the most of them either killed or wounded. <person>Lieut.
			H. B. Towles</person> was killed, also his sergeant, By the name of <person>Eli
			Edmondson</person>. The army was immediately <action side="american" unit="all">formed for Action</action>,
			which very soon began, it commenced on the right of the army,
			&amp; on the margin of the River, <person>Lieutenant Percy Pope</person> commanded
			<person>Capt. John Prices</person> company of artillery and he was the first officer
			that <action side="american">fired a shot</action> from our <weapon>howitzers</weapon>. Several of the first
			<weapon>shots was with shell</weapon> then he commenced with <weapon>grape &amp; cannister
			shot</weapon>. On front &amp; between the <side>indians</side> was <landscape>a large quantity of
			falling down Timber</landscape>, which was a shelter for the <side>indians</side>, where
			they remained some time, they would load &amp; fire then fall down &amp;
			load, then rise and fire again. A <action side="american">Charge</action> was very soon ordered
			by the <person>Commander in chief</person>, the <side>indians</side> soon <action side="confederation">retreated</action> they had
			a great many killed, <action side="confederation">they threw a number of there dead in the
			River</action>. <person>General Scott</person> <action side="american" unit="rear_guard">was ordered to try and seround the <side>indians</side></action>,
			but <action side="confederation">they got aprized of it</action> &amp; <action side="confederation">retreated</action> as fast as possible--

			<person>Capt. Robert Mis Campbell</person> &amp; <person>Lieutenant Harry B. Towles</person> were
			killed and several officers badly wounded. <person>Lieutenant Solomon
			Vanranceller</person> was shot in the right breast and taken to the <place>Generals
			Quarters</place>, <person>John OBrion</person> was with the front guard this morning,
			&amp; on the retreat he was shot in the low part of his back, the
			ball passed through the bottom of his Belly &amp; lodged in a certain
			part in front, in his P---- After <action side="american">entured the dead with the
			Honors of War</action> the army marched back to <place>Camp deposite</place>, we
			have heard that the <side>indians</side> <action side="confederation">Burnt poor <person>George May</person></action> who they
			took prisoner <date>19th inst.</date>
		</text>
	</battle_account>
	<battle_account id="clark" medium="journal">
	</battle_account>
</battle_accounts>