<?xml version="1.0"?>
	<ftAccounts>
		<ftAccount>
			<bibInfo>
				<title>Two Journals of the Kentucky Volunteers 1793 and 1794</title>
				<author>
					<lastName>Anonymous</lastName>
				</author>
				<editor>
					<givenName>Richard C.</givenName>
					<lastName>Knopf</lastName>
				</editor>
				<pubTitle>The Filson Club Historical Quarterly</pubTitle>
				<volume>27</volume>
				<issue>3</issue>
				<pubYear>1953</pubYear>
			</bibInfo>
			<account>
				<header>
					Wednesday 20
				</header>

				<para>
					<sentence>
            Clear,
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            The Baggage being Deposited, in the Fortification the Army moved at 6 in the following order <person id="">Capt Baker</person> &amp; <person id="">Capt Arnold</person>'s Companies under the Comd. of <person id="">Majr. Price</person> formd. the Front or Corps of observation. <person id="">Brigd. Genl. Todd</person> on the Left <person id="">Genl. Wilkinson</person> on the Margin of the River the artillery and bagage in the Centre <person id="">Genl Barbee</person> in the rear
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            the Ground for 5 miles high &amp; dry open Woods tall large Oaks at 45 Minutes past 8 the Front was attactd. by a number of Indians in the high Grass
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            They returnd. the fire and fell back to the Front of the Federal Army, which likewise fell back untill They Formed the line of Battle when they movd. on driving the Enemy before them the Cavelry chargd. here
          </sentence>
					<sentence>
            with the loss of the brave <person id="">Capt. M. Campbell</person> at this Time
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            <person id="">Genl Todd</person> Brigade was forming a line and immediately got into action after getting orders from Genl. Scott to dismount and move forwards in a lo swampy ground with a great dale of fallen Timber and thick brush with Hoop and black Ash bushes which rendred the place difficult to see a Man 10 yds
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            the action Continud all together 1 hour &amp; 20 Minutes with the Volunteers half an hour when the Indians and their white allies part British and some French retired in a very precipitate manner leaving their dead and some of their wounded on the Field
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            we moved back over the ground collectd. the wounded and moved to the Federal troops where they were haltd and had the wound dressd. and litters made to carry them in,
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            the Army then movd. forwarward within sight of the British Garison where the Army incampd on a high Bank in a thick Brush.
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            the Action was General and conducted with propriety and honour to the American Arms and Their Officer
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            in sight of the army was the River divided by a large Island well Cultivated with Corn &amp; beans and a number of Stacks of Hay which was a pleaseing sight to the Army but more particularly to the Volunteers that was across the River and bringing loads of Corn and Hay in one hour after the army got to the ground under the Guns of the British Garison
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            a smart Shower of Rain after the action.
          </sentence>
				</para>
			</account>
		</ftAccount>
		<ftAccount>
			<bibInfo>
				<title>From Greene Ville to Fallen Timbers, A Journal of the Wayne Campaign: July 28-September 14, 1794</title>
				<author>Anonymous [James Wilkinson]</author>
				<editor>Dwight L. Smith</editor>
				<pubName>Indiana Historical Society</pubName>
				<pubPlace>Indianapolis, IN</pubPlace>
				<pubYear>1952</pubYear>
			</bibInfo>
			<account>
				<header>
					August 20th 1794&#8212;
				</header>

				<para>
					<sentence>
            marched this morning about 7 O'Clk instead of the hour prescribed&#8212;
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            the troops divested of every species of baggage except their blankets&#8212;
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            the strength of the right Column was precisely 368 non commissioned-officers and privates&#8212;say of the 3 S Legn 250 and of the 1st S L. 118.
          </sentence>
					<sentence>
            the <person id="">C in C</person> ordered that the files should be doubled, and an interval of at least 200 yards from the centre column to be observed&#8212;
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            <person id="">Capt Springer</person> who led the right flank Rifle Men was ordered to observe an equal distance from the Column&#8212;
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            <person id="">the old Man</person> has forgot the Columns of Cavalry and light Infantry which must be between the main right Column and the Riflemen&#8212;
          </sentence>
          the regulation gives the right wing a front of 800 yards&#8212;this however is a pardonable&#8212;but his total deviation from the promise made yesterday to <person id="">Genl W.</person> to alter his disposition of march, is in every view unpardonable&#8212;
          <sentence>
            now if we had an enemy of military sagacity to contend with, <person id="">he</person> might with facility turn either our right or left flank, neither of which <person id="">I</person> am well assured have been examined more than two or three miles, and when we reach the extent of our march fall suddenly upon our baggage and provision, and by destroying them not only defeat the expedition but actually destroy the army, as we take but two days provision with us&#8212;
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            the face of the Country as we leave our encampment is agreable&#8212;
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            the day hot and clear&#8212;
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            the river bubbling over a Rocky sheet is bordered by a luxuriant prairie from 1/4 of a mile to 600 yards wide&#8212;
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            then we have a regular swell rising to the height of 80 or 100 feet covered with timber of various denominations which is sparse on the brow of this height, runing almost paralel with the River but inclining to the left&#8212;
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            the surface is flat&#8212;the wood thickens&#8212;becomes swampy and in some places almost impervious from the underwood and small growth&#8212;
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            it may be necessary to add that the high ground before spoken of which flanks the river in a direction nearly paralel,&#8212;is cut by many deep, steep and short ravines, runing nearly at right angles to the general course of this height&#8212;
          </sentence>
				</para>			
				<para>
					<sentence>
						having advanced about 4 miles <person id="">I</person> rode to the brow of this height with <person id="">Genl W.</person> who wanted to examine the position of his flank column and to get a view of <person id="">McKees</person> house on the East side of the river, and of the British Post with the flag flying below&#8212;
					</sentence>
					<sentence>
						<person id="">Genl W</person> made report of this to the <person id="">C in C</person> in the centre whose <person id="">aid de Camp Capt De B</person> and <person id="">Mr E. the Contractor</person> returned with him to take a view of the fort&#8212;
					</sentence>
					<sentence>
						when we reached the brow of the height, our attention was called by <person id="">Dr Heyward</person> to some horsemen who were pushing rapidly across the prairie about 1/4 of a mile in our front&#8212;
					</sentence>
					<sentence>
						it was first supposed they were a part of the volunteers in quest of plunder but observing them to alter their direction for our front and hearing at the same moment a few shot&#8212;
					</sentence>
					<sentence>
						<person id="">Genl W</person> rode up to <person id="">Capt De B</person> and requested him to hasten to the <person id="">C in C</person> and apprize him that our advance was attacked and retreating&#8212;
					</sentence>
					<sentence>
						<person id="">he</person> had scarcly made this observation when 40 or 50 of the mounted volunteers were discovered to be retreating directly toward us, in great confusion and before a faint fire of the enemy&#8212;
					</sentence>
					<sentence>
            the moment was critical as the troops had not yet received orders to form&#8212;
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            <person id="">Genl W.</person> hailed and halted the retreating party&#8212;reminded them of their name fame &amp; Country and exhorted them to turn and oppose the Enemy who were runing forward and throwing their shot at random and were by this within 150 yards&#8212;
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            several agreed to try and fight&#8212;
          </sentence>
          <sentence>
            but the <person id="">Generals</person> presence being necessarily called to the command of his wing the moment his back was turned they broke and resumed their flight thro the 1st Sub Legion then forming&#8212;
          </sentence>
				</para>

				<para>
					the Genl having brought up Gaines' Light Infantry and
					formed them in advance to check the enemy, repaired immediately
					to his left which was pressed by the Enemy&#8212;they were
					almost formed, tho in order, much too close&#8212;this defect
					was soon remedied and the troops stood with shouldered arms&#8212;when
					we reached the extreme left of the 3d S Legn we found
					Capt Miss Campbell, retreating with his troop in good Order&#8212;and
					also that Capt H Lewis who commanded the advanced
					light Infantry &amp; Rifle Men had fallen back and was mixed
					with the left of the right wing&#8212;we were at this time under a
					scattered fire of the Enemy at 100 yards distance&#8212;Genl W
					enquired of Capt Miss Campbell "what was the matter in front"
					he answered "every thing is confusion" and asked the Genl
					what he should do, who observed to him, that he not being
					under his command he could give him no orders, but recommended
					to him to fall back &amp; form squadron in his rear&#8212;the
					Genl then pushed towards the right, when we gained the right
					of the 3d S. L. then commanded by Cap Kingsbury,100 found
					the Enemy within 80 yards, Mr Gaines in the interim having
					changed his position by order from some person unknown and
					firing as warmly as the smallness of their number would permit&#8212;Kingsbury
					applied to the General for permission to
					charge but he having no orders or authority for that purpose
					forbid him &amp; commanded him to stand his ground—he then107
					ordered a Serjeant of Dragoons (neither of aids being near to
					him) to ride to Capt Springer &amp; inform him it was his desire
					that he should push forward and flank the Enemy on their
					left&#8212;returning to the centre Kingsbury again asked leave to
					charge, which was refused, as no order had been received or
					signal heard to that effect&#8212;at this instant Miss Campbell
					ordered the charge and dashing forward, passed the 1st Battn
					of the 3d S L. before the Genl could speak to him; in making
					this charge he was obliged to cross a steep ravine in our rear
					and to ascend a narrow point across which the troops of the
					right were formed&#8212;the ground in front was open and smooth
					and the Enemy at 80 or 100 yards distance&#8212;Genl W seeing
					the peril to which this movement exposed Miss Campbell,
					instantly (and without orders) directed a general charge&#8212;but
					being immediately informed that the height and strength of the
					grass in the prairie prevented the Riflemen from getting forward
					he sent his A D. C. Capt Shaumburgh to Capt Springer
					with directions to bring him into action on the high ground&#8212;and
					as the light Infantry under Gaines were similarly circumstanced,
					he presumed tho without authority to give similar
					orders to him&#8212;he also ventured to form Lieut. Webb with the
					first troop in his rear, with orders to follow the line at 150 yards
					distance&#8212;
				</para>

				<para>
					the charge succeeded as directed, the enemy making little
					or no resistance, but fell back from ravine to ravine loading &amp;
					firing at a considerable distance as we advanced&#8212;the fire was
					truly so light and the resistance so feeble, that we began to apprehend
					a deception and that the enemy had sent forward light
					parties to harrass and disorder us, and to draw us in that Condition
					into the hands of their main body&#8212;under this impression
					Genl W rode to the C in C whom he found in the centre and
					suggested to him his apprehensions and the propriety of halting
					and forming&#8212;he told him, to do so&#8212;but the intention was
					defeated by an increased fire from the enemy on the left&#8212;the
					charge was therefore renewed after a momentary and partial
					halt which had not given time to form the line&#8212;during the
					pause the Genl sent his extra aid de Camp, Lieut C. Smith109
					with a message to the C in C&#8212;he sought but could not find him
					and returning received a shot in his right breast which by the
					faculty is deemed to be mortal&#8212;this affair had lasted nearly an
					hour&#8212;the artillery were left behind, the light Infantry and
					Rifle Men could not get up into the action and the troops were
					much disordered&#8212;the charge still continued &amp; the fire of the
					enemy began to slacken&#8212;At this moment Lieut Covington110
					of the Dragoons was observed in our front charging from the
					left to our right with 6 or 8 Dragoons, and the ground being
					even and the wood open, having gained our right near the brow
					of the height he wheeled to the left and was charging to the
					front, the enemy being then in view and retreating&#8212;Genl W
					sent his A. D. C. Mr Shamburgh to order Lieut Webb to
					charge&#8212;and called to Covington to halt, but as his voice could
					not reach him and seeing him rushing upon destruction&#8212;(as
					he would with 6 or 8 men have been in with the Enemy long
					before Webb could get up) in order to save him, he determined
					to make a decisive tho not very justifiable attempt&#8212;he clapped
					spurs to his horse &amp; runing at full speed about 250 yards in
					front of his line and close upon the rear of the Enemy, passed
					and halted Covington for a moment&#8212;this gave time for Webb
					to shew himself and support&#8212;in making this movement the
					Genl had thrown himself between Covington and a Savage
					who presented his piece at him but did not fire, altho' he passed
					within a few paces of him&#8212;Covington seeing his danger,
					charged this son of the woods, sword in hand and killed him
					on the spot&#8212;the Genl having accomplished his purpose which
					was to save or to give a fair chance to a gallant officer and an
					amiable man, wheeled and rejoined his command which was
					still advancing—mean time Covington &amp; Webb kept up the
					charge and we saw no more of the Enemy&#8212;Covington killed
					two and Webb one Indian with their own hands&#8212;the retreat
					soon after beat, when we halted and formed in one line&#8212;
				</para>

				<para>
					in the commencement of the action Capt Shamburgh
					(whom the Genl had left at the head of his Column to receive
					orders for him while he road to the right) having heard a
					firing in front, rode to the centre and apprised the C in C of our
					being attacked&#8212;who replyed, "Yes, I heard it, there was 6 or
					8 Guns"&#8212;the other rejoined in surprise "6 or 8 Sir! I have
					heard at least 150 shot" and turned off in disgust&#8212;at this
					instant the Militia were discovered to be flying in front&#8212;		some
					person near the C in C then observed that they were
					runing and asked what was to be done after a short pause&#8212;the
					C. in C. bawled out "prepare to receive the Enemy in front in
					two Lines"&#8212;but his voice could not be heard 150 yards at
					which distance each Column was from the centre and this was
					the only order we received from him prior to or during the
					action&#8212;Col. H informs also, that he received no order during
					the action, or for forming&#8212;Genl W formed in one line&#8212;he in
					two&#8212;consequently the 2d S L. scarcely got into the action and
					the 4th S L was at one period nearly out flanked&#8212;the light
					Infantry &amp; Dragoons who were selected and reserved for the C
					in C's special command, acted I am well assured, without orders
					from him&#8212;notwithstanding the wise precaution which have
					been taken by frittering up the army, into guards &amp; Detachments,
					we were fairly surprised, &amp; the Enemy within Gun-Shot
					of us before we were formed&#8212;it is unquestionable with me,
					that if the Enemy had struck with their whole force at any
					point of our army&#8212;instead of attempting with 900 men to
					form a line of two miles they would have penetrated and if they
					pleased passed thro us, making great havock at least&#8212;all the
					pompous and prolix orders of battle, heretofore issued and received,
					were here entirely neglected, not a word was uttered
					about forming the square&#8212;the light Infantry, Rifle Men &amp;
					Cavalry attacked immediately&#8212;fell back to the Columns and
					were not fixed upon total extirpation&#8212;neither of these Corps
					were embodied and they were in general left to exercise their
					own discretion&#8212;yet when I saw the C in C he appeared tranquil&#8212;no
					attempt was made to profit by our victory&#8212;altho'
					very few of the volunteers had been engaged&#8212;and a great
					proportion of our Dragoons were in vigorous plight&#8212;instead
					of letting loose 1700 men upon the disordered rear of the
					dismayed fugitives, we made a dead halt the moment the fire
					of the enemy ceased and they were not pursued one single step,
					except by the Dragoons under Covington and Webb&#8212;the
					Command of whom Genl W. had assumed&#8212;this looks more
					like unto a drawn battle than a victory&#8212;if Miss Campbell
					charged by order, he was sacrificed&#8212;if of his own accord he
					threw away his life&#8212;his loss is to be regretted as he was a
					good officer&#8212;
				</para>

				<para>
					this affair which does not deserve the name of a Battle
					began at 10 O Clk and the troops halted at 5 minutes after 11
					O'Clk&#8212;we remained on the ground untill 4 O'Clk&#8212;no order
					was given by the C in C to collect and bury the dead or to
					recover the axes and mens blanketts, which had been dropt in
					the begining of the fight&#8212;Individuals sought for their
					wounded friends&#8212;and Genl W. without order, made a small
					detachment for this purpose&#8212;these when collected were
					ordered back to deposit Camp under the Escort of a Body of
					volunteers and the army moved forward at [blank] O'Clk to
					encamp on the Bank of the Miami in sight of and about one
					mile distant from the British fort&#8212;several of the wounded
					who were left with the volunteers, were brought back into
					Camp after dark, &amp; about 8 O'Clk this evening Genl Todd
					brought in a wounded man who had been found on the field by
					the militia&#8212;the C in C seems disposed to confer the honor
					of the day upon the left Wing or rather 4th Sub Legion&#8212;a
					small number only of the volunteers got into the action on the
					left and behaved well&#8212;a partial and impolitic issue of whiskey
					was made after the affair was over, of which the volunteers
					were excluded from partaking&#8212;the C in C this evening swore
					that "he had seen in front of the 4th S Legn at one view, 400
					Savages as naked by by the eternal God! as they came out
					of their mothers Wombs"&#8212;a french man, painted and dressed,
					as a Savage, was found after the affair terminated, conceal near
					the river bank armed with a double barrelled fusee&#8212;he is
					recognised by Col. Hamtramck as a former resident of Ouittanon&#8212;he
					says he is a trader&#8212;that he arrived at the British
					Fort, the evening before&#8212;that his boat had been taken to bring
					up provision from Cedar Island and that he had been forced
					to go into the Battle tho' he had not fired his gun&#8212;which from
					examination appeared to be true&#8212;he informs that the Body
					opposed to us consisted of 900 Indians about 40 White men&#8212;	that
					the Indians were averse to the action but that Elliot &amp;
					McKee who were engaged in person dragged them into it
					telling them, they need but make a trial of what they could
					do&#8212;he says the Women &amp; children had been removed a considerable
					distance below the fort and that he expects the Indians
					will draw off and wait the issue of an attack upon that place&#8212;he
					adds that messages had been sent to all the nations to
					assemble&#8212;that the Chippiways had refused to come and he
					did not know what might be the determination of the other
					Nations&#8212;he further says that an express had been sent to
					Niagara for a reinforcement to the Garrison&#8212;that [t]he whole
					force of the British Garrison is 250 and that 50 of these are
					sick&#8212;It is worthy of remark here that this evening after the
					army halted, the C in C got into a violent passion with Capt
					Ford, whose men warm with fatigue &amp; nearly exhausted had
					pulled off their Coats&#8212;in the course of his ravings, he addressed
					himself to a drummer who happened to be present and
					said&#8212;"I have fought under the hotest and the coldest suns
					and such a thing never was permitted nor shall it now be done&#8212;it
					is damned cowardly"&#8212;
				</para>

				<para>
					Without disparagement to any person the Individual act of
					greatest Gallantry this day exhibited on the right, was performed
					by Lieut. Shamburgh A D C to Brg Genl Wilkinson&#8212;this
					officer being sent by his Genl with an order to the light
					troops of the right flank&#8212;and perceiving as he led on part of
					the light Infantry under Ensign Claiborne, a party of savages
					firing from a Covert of Bushes and high grass on the Margin
					of the Prairie&#8212;he, sword in hand dashed into the thickett,
					gained the rear of an Indian warrior and the pursuit actually
					actually forced him upon the bayonets of Claiborne's
					party&#8212;
				</para>

				<para>
					It is also a tribute due to Mr R Elliot the Contractor to
					declare&#8212;that he so far participated in the action, as to lead two
					companies of the Kentucky volunteers, who were lost and
					flying, up to the fire of the enemy&#8212;an office which few
					men in his Station would have undertaken.
				</para>
			</account>
		</ftAccount>
		<ftAccount>
			<bibInfo>
				<title>A Sketch of the Early Adventures of William Sudduth in Kentucky</title>
				<author>William Sudduth</author>
				<editor>Lucien Beckner</editor>
				<pubTitle>The History Quarterly</pubTitle>
				<volume>2</volume>
				<issue>2</issue>
				<pubYear>1928</pubYear>
			</bibInfo>
			<account>
				<header>
					
				</header>

				<para>
					...The next morning Orders were for
					the detachment of Spies to march by sun rise but we were
					prevented by a thunderstorm coming on. It cleared off about
					Eight oclock and we proceeded on untill we came within
					about half a mile of where the Indians had caused us to retreat
					the day before.
				</para>

				<para>
					The detachment got water &amp; stript off all unnecessary
					clothing. It was usual with us to guard against surprise, to
					keep two men in front of each line about one hundred yards.
					We generally called them out in rotation as they stood on the
					list. I observed to the men not to dispute about who was next
					on duty that this was the day to gain honor and nearly half
					my line turned out. I recalled them all except two Thomas
					Moore &amp; William Steele. They moved on briskley &amp; had not
					advanced more than one hundred yards untill they fell into an
					ambuscade and were both shot down. We advanced briskley
					untill we came within twenty yards of the Indians &amp; received
					their full fire. Moore was not dead &amp; was taken up &amp; put on a
					horse untill he died. Maj. Price then Ordered a retreat &amp; lead
					it about sixty steps. The course we took lead us along the
					head of the Indian line &amp; they fired on us with a tremendious
					roar at a verry short distance. We passed that body of Indians
					&amp; saw another party advancing upon us headed by several
					horsemen, Maj. Price then Ordered us to halt &amp; fight them. At
					that instant some of the Indian horsemen fired upon us at about
					forty steps distance. Maj Price then returned their fire which
					caused them to pause. I then fired at one of the horsemen who
					instantly fell from his horse. Lucas Hood &amp; Harry Martin were
					one on each side of me with their guns cocked &amp; up to their faces
					to shoot, but he fell so quick as to save their fire. We then
					received a verry heavy fire from the foot men. The Maj.
					then Ordered a retreat to the main army which was briskly
					advancing to support us.
				</para>

				<para>
					We had retreated some distance when a man called out to
					me by name that we were leaving a wounded man. I looked
					back &amp; saw the man running after us &amp; the Indians in full persuit
					after him. They were about seventy yards behind us &amp; the
					wounded man about half way between the two lines. I immediately
					stoped my horse &amp; called to the men who would go
					back with me. Maj. Price was close by me; he neither said
					go or stay. I turned back &amp; five men went with me. When we
					met the wounded man the Indians were from thirty to thirty
					five steps from him. They immediately droped in the weeds
					&amp; bushes &amp; commenced a heavy fire on us. I turned my horse
					round and the wounded man tried twice to jump behind me &amp;
					failed. I then turned the side of my horse to him &amp; put out
					my foot for him to get up in that manner in which he failed also.
					William Richie from Mason &amp; Harvey Martin from Clarke lit
					from their horses &amp; lifted the man up behind me during which
					time the Indians kept up an incessant fire at us at about thirty
					or thirty five steps distance. I could see into the muzel of many
					of their guns when they raised them to fire on us. The bark of
					the trees flew into our faces just as they had put the man up
					behind me &amp; the man to my right hand he sliped off, the Indians
					shot my horse. The ball passed between the thy of the man
					behind me &amp; my own &amp; cut the hind part of the pad of my sadle.
					The men that were with me then left me and the horse became
					unmanageable; he reared up three times &amp; would not move out
					of the place. The Indians by this time advanced with their
					tomahawks drawn verry close to me and I believe if my horse
					had have seen the Indian horses he would have run to them but
					fortunately he discovered the horses of the men that had left
					me and followed them. I gave him the spur &amp; pushed him on
					the blood gushing out of the wound, his mouth &amp; nose verry fast.
					He ran about one hundred and fifty yards &amp; stoped. I leaped
					off him &amp; left the man, who informed me afterwards that the
					horse fell immediately after I left him. We had got far anough
					in advance of the Indians for the wounded man to save himself.
				</para>

				<para>
					When I left the horse'I ran on after my party &amp; they halted
					for me. I got up behind one of them and soon met the front of
					the Army coming up to our support. I then loaded my gun.
					A man by the name of White dismounted &amp; gave me up his horse.
					He had heard me receive orders that morning to endeavor to
					turn the right flank of the Indians &amp; said I could not perform
					the service on foot. I immediately mounted the horse &amp; returned
					towards the front of the Indians. I collected about
					thirty or thirty five of the Spies, part belonging to each company.
					I shaped my course course in front of the Indian line &amp;
					passed between them &amp; our Army, as they approached each other,
					untill they came so close to each other that a Company of
					regulars on our extreme right had to open to the right &amp; left to
					let us pass. As we passed the fire of both Armies closed after
					us; the Indians were passing on endeavoring to turn our right
					wing. I continued in the same direction within gunshot of them
					and several times halted to fire on them but they continued to
					try to out flank us. I at last pushed on untill I passed their left
					&amp; wheeled around their extreme point of their left wing. They
					then raised a schrill hallow which was answered in the same
					manner back along their line that ended the battle in less than
					two minutes. The firing ceased &amp; the Indians retreated. It is
					stated by some that the Indians were persued but it was not the
					case.
				</para>

				<para>
					The army remained some time on the battle ground and then
					encamped near the British garrison of about three hundred men
					commanded by Maj. Campbell. That evening &amp; the following
					two days the men destroyed the corn that stood near the garrison,
					burnt their hay, &amp; gardens, &amp; every out house, among
					otherst the house of Col. MeKee, an Indian trader. The next
					day after the battle the spies were sent down the river about seven
					miles on the direction the Indians had retreated. In many
					places for several yards in weadth they had tread down the
					weeds like a log had been roled over it. We discovered no
					Indians &amp; returned to Camp. Our loss in battle was about one
					hundred in killed &amp; wounded. We had five killed in our Company,
					but none wounded that survived the first night. It was
					reported that the Americans got forty two scalps. It was supposed
					from appearances that many more were killed &amp; taken off
					or threw into a pond near where we fought....
				</para>
			</account>
		</ftAccount>
		<ftAccount>
			<bibInfo>
				<author>William Clark</author>
				<editor>R. C. McGrane</editor>
				<title>William Clark's Journal of General Wayne's Campaign</title>
				<pubTitle>The Mississippi Valley Historical Review</pubTitle>
				<volume>1</volume>
				<issue>3</issue>
				<pubYear>1914</pubYear>
			</bibInfo>
			<account>
				<header>
					20th August 94&#8212;
				</header>

				<para>
					A sower of Rain prevented our move at the
					houre appointed, but we took up the Line of March at 7 o'Clock and
					found the way extremely bad, much embarrassed by the thickness of
					the woods on the left and by a number of Steep Reviens on the Right,
					after proceeding about 2 hours our Spies &amp; advance guard Discovered
					the Enemy and received their fire, but with inconsiderable Loss were
					driven back and joined the main Body of the Army, by this time the
					Right division, Comd^{ed} by Genl. Wilkinson felt the effects of the Enemeys
					fire, they was immediately formed &amp; returned the fire, at this period
					Capt. Campbell troop made a charge in which he fell &amp; his Troop immediately
					proceeded through surported by the Infantry's charge which
					oblidged the enemey to quit theire position and look for more advantagous
					ground. on our Left &amp; they made an exertion to gaine that Flank
					but Col^o Hamtramck who commanded in that Quarter was perpared &amp;
					gave them so warm a recption as made theire Situation here as disagreeable
					as that on the Right, and the charge both on the Right &amp; left both
					became Genl. &amp; the Enemy was repulsed with precipation; The charge
					of the Cavelry closed the seene in front &amp; drove the Enemey 3/4 of a
					mile at the same instant, The Riflemen &amp; Light Infantry, receved a
					most heavy fire, on the extreem left flank, The Entrepid Lieut. Towls
					fell at this fire, We drove the Enemy for about one mile directly out,
					with the Loss of Lieut. Towls &amp; a fiew Infantry on our Side, in this
					quater was Killed 3 white men &amp; several Indians mostly by the Riflemen.
					the Troops were now refreshed with 1/2 a gill of Whiskey which
					they much required as the action continued more then an houre, the
					greater part of which time they were in full Speed pressing the Enemey&#8212;after
					remaining on this ground a fiew hours Dureing which time the
					wounded were Brought in Dressed &amp;c we proceeded within about one
					mile of the British Garrison and there took up our Encampment.
				</para>

				<para>
					I shall now make a fiew observations or reflections on the Buisness of
					this day. Had the Enemey for once forsaken theire long established
					mode of fighting (Viz) that of extending theire lines so as to gaine the
					flanks of theire advasary&#8212;for by this means they so weakened themselves
					in all points as not to be able to make but a feable resistance in
					any one, much less beat &amp; confuse the lines of theire opposers, which in
					this case they might have easily done, had they kept themselves compact
					and advanced with Judgement. (I say had the Enemey been formed in
					tolerable close orders and advanced in the first instance, close on the heals
					of our retireing Spies &amp; Advanced guard, I am Satisfied they would
					have made a Breach in any part of our Columns as our Front was so extended
					as to render the whole in any one part, unequal to the resistants
					of a well formed body rapidly advancing on them, besides our orders or
					mode of Formation required very considerable time to performe the perparitory
					Evolutions: on the other hand, had the Kentucky Volunters
					(who composed half of our forces) been so disposed of as to have
					gained the reare of the Enemy soon after they commenced the attack,
					Then I am Satisfied we should had the pleasure of seeing every Head of
					this dreaded Hydra at our feet; but from theire Situation or (as some
					say for the want of orders) they were so far from gaining this grand
					position, that not more then 300 out of 1500 well mounted Riflemen were
					ever brought to action, and they but a fiew moments. Cannot but be
					astonished when the world informed that the Comd^r in Chief had been
					told on the day previous to the action, by an officere of Rank an credebillity
					(Maj^r Price of the Volunteers who comm^d a sort of Independant
					partizan-corps and had been sent for the Express purpose) that the
					Enemey were laying in wait for us &amp; formed in Such a possition" &amp; also
					gave His Excellency an exact Discription of the ground I say, the
					whole world cannot but be surprised that the Comd^r in Chief did not
					availe himself of this advantage &amp; by throwing the Voluntiers in the
					reare of the Enemey &amp; eventually cut off theire retreat: but so far was
					his Excel^{cy} from thus putting an end to this expensive war (I believe
					that the atack of the Enemey at the time it happined was actually a matter
					of Surprise to almost every officer in the army&#8212;The Bodies of Capt.
					Campbell &amp; Lieutenant Towles (the only officers killed) were entered
					immediately after the action. The whole ammount of the Killed on our
					part were 240 the loss of the Enemey not precisely ascertained but not
					more than 30 or 40 were found Dead, and a fiew Canadians one was
					taken prisoner, who was a treader amoung the Indians, and says they opposed
					us with about 900 Indians &amp; 150 Canadians.
				</para>
			</account>
		</ftAccount>
		<ftAccount>
			<bibInfo>
				<author>Thomas Taylor Underwood</author>
				<title>Journal, Thomas Taylor Underwood, March 26, 1792 to March 18, 1800: An Old Soldier in Wayne's Army</title>
				<pubName>The Society of Colonial Wars in the State of Ohio</pubName>
				<pubPlace>Cincinnati, OH</pubPlace>
				<pubYear>1945</pubYear>
			</bibInfo>
			<account>
				<header>
					Camp Deposite, the 20th August 1794&#8212;
				</header>

				<para>
					This morning the army was under arms, at day light and our
					line of march arranged. Lietenant Hary Beverly Towles was
					detailed to take command of the front guard, he was ordered to
					march on in front, the main army commenced there march,
					General Charles Scott with his mounted Volunteers were placed
					in the rear. After marching 3 or 4 miles the front guard was
					fired on, &amp; the most of them either killed or wounded. Lieut.
					H. B. Towles was killed, also his sergeant, By the name of Eli
					Edmondson. The army was immediately formed for Action,
					which very soon began, it commenced on the right of the army,
					&amp; on the margin of the River, Lieutenant Percy Pope commanded
					Capt. John Prices company of artillery and he was the first officer
					that fired a shot from our howitzers. Several of the first
					shots was with shell then he commenced with grape &amp; cannister
					shot. On front &amp; between the indians was a large quantity of
					falling down Timber, which was a shelter for the indians, where
					they remained some time, they would load &amp; fire then fall down &amp;
					load, then rise and fire again. A Charge was very soon ordered
					by the Commander in chief, the indians soon retreated they had
					a great many killed, they threw a number of there dead in the
					River. General Scott was ordered to try and seround the indians,
					but they got aprized of it &amp; retreated as fast as possible&#8212;
				</para>

				<para>
					Capt. Robert Mis Campbell &amp; Lieutenant Harry B. Towles were
					killed and several officers badly wounded. Lieutenant Solomon
					Vanranceller was shot in the right breast and taken to the Generals
					Quarters, John OBrion was with the front guard this morning,
					&amp; on the retreat he was shot in the low part of his back, the
					ball passed through the bottom of his Belly &amp; lodged in a certain
					part in front, in his P&#8212;&#8212; After entured the dead with the
					Honors of War the army marched back to Camp deposite, we
					have heard that the indians Burnt poor George May who they
					took prisoner 19th inst.
				</para>
			</account>
		</ftAccount>
		<ftAccount>
			<bibInfo>
				<author>Randolph</author>
				<editor>Richard C. Knopf</editor>
				<title>A Precise Journal of General Wayne's Last Campaign in the year 1794, against the western Indians, taken down in the course of the campaign: With an account of an attack made of an attack made on Fort Recovery, by the Indians, on the 30th June preceding.</title>
				<pubTitle>American Antiquarian Society</pubTitle>
				<pubYear>1954</pubYear>
			</bibInfo>
			<account>
				<header>
					AUGUST 20th.
				</header>

				<para>
					Prevented from marching this Morning at the appointed Hour
					by Rain; but a 7 o'Clock the Line of March is taken up and continued
					in the most perfect Order for four Miles, when a Firing
					commenced in Front; in a few Moments our advanced Parties
					were compelled to retire by a superior Number. In the Interim
					the Legion was formed in two Lines, but the Commander in Chief
					finding the Enemy were gaining our left Flank, ordered the Rear
					Line to advance to support the Front&#8212;This done, and the Whole
					formed now in one sustaining front Line, a Charge was ordered,
					in which the Enemy were routed and compelled to retire one Mile
					in one Hour. When the Pursuit was left, the Legion halted and
					refreshed with an Issue of some Spirits&#8212;our Killed and Wounded
					collected, the former enterred, the latter dressed and sent to Camp
					Deposit. Among the Killed was that goodj brave, gallant and
					intrepid Captain Robert Mis Campbell, of the second Troop
					Light Dragoons, and then commanding Officer of the Cavalry,
					who fell in a Charge on the Enemy in an early Part of the Action;
					by which the Legion was deprived of one of its bravest Officers,
					before he had an Opportunity of rendering his Country those
					Services which were to be expected from his Bravery. It would
					be vain for Abilities like mine to attempt to describe the deceased
					Captain Campbell's Virtues; but to do Justice to his Memory I
					cannot avoid observing, he was possessed of every Qualification
					which constitutes the Gentleman, the Officer and a good Man:
					and as he was when living generally loved, now that he is dead
					I believe he is as generally lamented.
				</para>

				<para>
					Lieutenant Henry B. Towles, a brave and gallant Officer of the
					4th Sub-Legion Light-Infantry, was also killed in the Course of
					this Action, and several other intrepid Officers wounded.
				</para>

				<para>
					During the Halt of the Legion at this Place, and while the right
					Flankers were in Advance of the Army half a Mile, a Canadian was
					taken, who was painted and dressed like an Indian Warrior. In
					one half Hour the Whole moved some Distance father down the
					River and within half a Mile of the Fort, where we were halted
					and encamped under the Guns of said Garrison, from which a
					Flag was this Afternoon received&#8212;its Purport unknown.
				</para>

				<para>
					Advanced six Miles this Day.
				</para>
			</account>
		</ftAccount>
		<ftAccount>
			<bibInfo>
				<author>John Boyer</author>
				<title>A Journal of Wayne's Campaign: Being an Authentic Daily Record of the most Important Occurrences during the Campaign of Major General Anthony Wayne, against the Northwestern Indians; Commencing on the 28th day of July, and ending on the 2d day of November, 1794; including an account of the great battle of August 20th.</title>
				<pubName>Jno. F. Uhlhorn</pubName>
				<pubPlace>Cincinnati, OH</pubPlace>
				<pubYear>1866</pubYear>
			</bibInfo>
			<account>
				<header>
					Camp in sight of a British garrison, on the Miamis of the Lake,
					August 20th, 1794&#8212;one hundred and fifty miles from Greenville.
				</header>
				<para>
				  This day the legion, after depositing every kind of baggage,
				  took up the line of march at 7 o'clock, and continued their
				  route down the margin of the river, without making any
				  discovery, until 11 o'clock, when the front guard, which was
				  composed of mounted volunteers, were fired on by the enemy.
				  The guard retreated in the utmost confusion through the front
				  guard of the regulars, commanded by Captain Cook and
				  Lieutenant Steele, who, in spite of their utmost exertion,
				  made a retreat. These fell in with the left of Captain
				  Howell Lewis' company of light infantry and threw that part
				  of the men into confusion, which Captain Lewis observing, he
				  ordered the left of his company to retreat about forty yards,
				  where he formed them and joined the right, which had stood
				  their ground. They continued in this position until they
				  were joined by part of Captain Springer's battalion of riflemen,
				  which was nearly fifteen minutes after the firing commenced,
				  who drove the enemy that had attempted to flank us on the
          right. Nearly at the same time, the right column came up,
          and the charge was sounded&#8212;the enemy gave way and fired
          scattering shots as they run off.
				</para>

        <para>
  				About the time the right column came up, a heavy firing
			    took place on the left, which lasted but a short time, the
			    enemy giving way in all quarters, which left us in possession
			    of their dead to the number of forty. Our loss was thirty
			    killed and one hundred wounded. Among the former we
			    have to lament the loss of <person id="">Captain Miss Campbell</person> of the
			    dragoons, and <person id="">Lieutenant Henry B. Fowles</person> of the 4th sub-legion;
			    and of the latter, <person id="">Captains Prior</person> of the first, <person id="">Slough</person>
			    of the fourth, and <person id="">Van Rensselaer</person> of the dragoons, also
			    <person id="">Lieutenant Campbell Smith</person> of the fourth sub-legion. The
			    whole loss of the enemy cannot at present be ascertained, but
			    it is more than probable it must have been considerable, for
			    we pursued them with rapidity for nearly two miles. As to
			    the number of the enemy engaged in this action, opinions are
			    so various that I am at a loss to know what to say; the most
			    general opinion is one thousand five hundred, one-third of
			    which are supposed to be Canadians; I am led to believe this
			    number is not over the mark. After the troops had taken
			    some refreshment, the legion continued their route down the
			    river, and encamped in sight of the British garrison. One
			    Canadian fell into our hands, who we loaded with irons.
			  </para>
			</account>
		</ftAccount>
		<ftAccount>
			<bibInfo>
				Wayne's General Orders
			</bibInfo>
			<account>
				<header>
					Head Quarters, Deposit Camp, 19th August 1794
				</header>

				<para>
					The Army will March tomorrow Morning at five OClock agreeable to the constant order of March, with this difference; That the Columns shall March two deep and in as close Order as Circumstances will admit of, being totally divested of Baggage, the Center will be left free for the Artillery and spare Ammunition&#8212;
				</para>

				<para>
					The Officers and Men shall dress in their proper Uniforms&#8212;The Troops will on the March be ordered occasionally to form in two lines to receive the Enemy in front&#8212;The Manoeuvers will be the same as constantly Practiced; should Circumstances render it Necessary to Order the Troops to strip&#8212;it will be done but by the Commander in Chief, but it shall not be done but by his positive Order&#8212;
				</para>

				<para>
					Captain Pike will take Command of the Camp and every Department are to be subject to his Order&#8212;
				</para>
			</account>
		</ftAccount>
		<ftAccount>
			<bibInfo>
				<title>Anthony Wayne's Letter to Knox, Aug. 28, 1794</title>
			</bibInfo>
			<account>
				<header>
					Head Quarters
					Grand Glaize 28th Augt. 1794
				</header>

				<opening>
					Sir
				</opening>

				<para>
					It's with infinite pleasure that I now announce to you the brilliant success of the Federal army under my Command in a General action with the combined force of the Hostile Indians &amp; a considerable number of the Volunteers &amp; Militia of Detroit on the 20th Instant, on the banks of the Miamis, in the vicinity of the British post &amp; Garrison at the foot of the rapids.
				</para>

				<para>
					The army advanced from this place on the 15th &amp; arrived at Roche de Bout, on the 18th. the 19th we were employed in making a temporary post for the reception of our stores &amp; baggage, &amp; in reconnoitering the position of the enemy who were encamped behind a thick brushy wood and the British Fort.
				</para>

				<para>
					At 8. OClock on the morning of the 20th the army again advanced in Columns agreeably to the standing order of March—the Legion on the right, its right flank cover'd by the Miamis, One Brigade of Mounted Volunteers on the left, under Brigr General Todd, &amp; the other in the rear under Brigr Genl Barbee, a select Battalion of Mounted Volunteers moved in front of the Legion commanded by Major Price, who was directed to keep sufficiently advanced, so as to give timely notice for the troops to form in case of Action.
				</para>

				<para>
					It being yet undetermined whether the Indians wou'd decide on peace or war:
				</para>

				<para>
					After advancing about Five miles, Major Price's corps received so severe a fire from the enemy, who were secreted in the woods &amp; high grass, as to compel them to retreat.
				</para>

				<para>
					The Legion was immediately formed in two lines principally in a close thick wood which extended for miles on our left &amp; for very considerable distance in front, the ground being cover'd with old fallen timber probably occasioned by a tornado, which render'd it impracticable for the Cavalry to act with effect, &amp; afforded the enemy the most favorable covert for their mode of warfare these savages were formed in three lines within supporting distance of each other &amp; extending near two miles at right angles with the River  I soon discover'd from the weight of the fire, &amp; extent of their Lines that the enemy were in full force in front in possession of their favorite ground &amp; endeavoring to turn our left flank, I therefore gave orders for the second line to advance to support the first, &amp; directed Major Genl Scott to gain &amp; turn the right flank of the savages with the whole of the Mounted Volunteers by a circuitous route, at the same time I ordered the front line to advance &amp; charge with trailed arms &amp; rouse the Indians from their coverts at the point of the bayonet, followed by a br[i]sk charge, so as not to give time to load again I also order'd Capt Mis Campbell who commanded the Legionary Cavalry to turn the left flank of the Enemy next the river &amp; which afforded a favorable field for that Corps to act in,
				</para>

				<para>
					All those orders were obeyed with spirit &amp; promptitude, but such was the impetuosity of the charge by the first line of Infantry&#8212;that the Indians &amp; Canadian Militia &amp; Volunteers were drove from all their Coverts in so short a time, that altho every possible exertion was used by the Officers of the second line of the Legion &amp; by Generals Scott, Todd &amp; Barbee of the Mounted Volunteers, to gain their proper position's but part of each cou'd get up in season to participate in the Action, the enemy being drove in the course of One hour more than two miles thro' the thick woods already mentioned, by less than one half their Numbers, from Every account the Enemy amounted to two thousand combatants, the troops actually engaged against them were short of nine hundred; [illegible] Savages with their allies abandoned themselves to flight &amp; dispersed with terror &amp; dismay, leaving our victorious army in full &amp; quiet possession of the field of  battle, which terminated under the influence of the Guns of the British Garrison as you will observe by the enclosed correspondence between Major Campbell the Commandant &amp; myself upon the Occasion
				</para>

				<para>
					The bravery &amp; Conduct of every Officer belonging to the Army from the Generals down to the Ensigns merits my highest approbation; there were however some whose rand &amp; situation placed their Conduct in a very conspicuous point of view, and which I observed with pleasure &amp; the most lively gratitude, among whom I must beg leave to mention Brigt Genl Wilkinson &amp; Colo Hamtramck the Commandants fo the right &amp; left wings of the Legion whose brave example inspired the troops, to them I must add the names of my faithful &amp; Gallant Aids de Camp Captains DeButts &amp; T Lewis &amp; Lieut Harrison who with the Adjt General Major Mills, rendered the most essential services by communicating my orders in every direction &amp; by their Conduct &amp; bravery exciting the troops to press for Victory; Lieut Covington upon whom the Command of the Cavalry now devolved cut down two savages with his own hand &amp; Lieut Webb one in turn &amp; [illegible] the Enemies left flank.
				</para>

				<para>
					The wounds received by Captains Slough &amp; Prior &amp; Lieut Campbell Smith (an extra aid de Camp to Genl Wilkinson) of Legionary Infantry &amp; Capt Van Renselaer of the Dragoons, Captain Rawlins Lieut McKenny &amp; Ensign Duncan of the Mounted Volunteers, bear honorable testimony of their bravery &amp; Conduct.
				</para>

				<para>
					Captains H Lewis &amp; Brock with their Companies of Light Infantry had to sustain an unequal combat for some time which they supported with fortitude, in fact every Officer &amp; soldier who had an Opportunity to come into action displayed that true braver which will always insure success: &amp; here permit e to declare that I never discover'd more true spirit &amp; anxiety for Acton than appeared to pervade the whole of the Mounted Volunteers, &amp; I am well persuaded that had the Enemy maintained their favorite ground but for one half hour longer they wou'd have most severely felt the prowess of that Corps
				</para>

				<para>
					But whilst I pay this just tribute to the living I must not forget the Gallant dead, among whom we have to lament the early death of those worthy &amp; brave Officers Capt Mis Campbell of the Dragoons &amp; Lieut Towles of the Light Infantry of the Legion who fell in the first Charge.
				</para>

				<para>
					enclosed is a particular return of the killed &amp; Wounded&#8212;the loss of the Enemy was more that double to that of the Federal Army&#8212;the woods were strewed for a considerable distance with the dead bodies of Indians &amp; their white Auxiliaries, the latter armed with British Muskets &amp; bayonets:
				</para>

				<para>
					After remaining three days &amp; nights on the banks of the Miamis in front of the Field of battle during which time all the Houses &amp; Corn fields were consumed &amp; destroyed for a considerable distance both above &amp; below Fort Miamis as well as within pistol shot of the Garrison who were compeled to remain tacit spectators to this general devastation &amp; Conflagration; among which were the Houses stores &amp; property of Colo McKee the British Indian Agent &amp; principal stimulator of the War now existing between the United States &amp; the savages
				</para>

				<para>
					The army returned to this place on the 27th by easy marches laying waste the Villages &amp; Corn fields for about Fifty miles on each side fo the Miamis&#8212;there remains yet a number of Villages &amp; a great Quantity of Corn to be consume or destroyed upon Au Glaize &amp; the Miamis above this place which will be effected in the course of a few days, In the interim we shall improve Fort Defiance &amp; as soon as the Escort return[s] with the necessary supplies form Greeneville &amp; Fort Recovery&#8212;the Army will proceed to the Miami Villages in order to accomplish the Object of the Campaign.
				</para>

				<para>
					It is however not improbable that the Enemy may make one more desperate effort against the Army&#8212;as it is said that a Reinforcement was hourly expected at Fort Miamis from Niagra, as well as Numerous tribes of Indians living on the Margins &amp; Islands of the Lakes: This is a business rathar to be wished for than dreaded whilst the army remain in force&#8212;their Numbers will only tend to confuse the Savages&#8212; &amp; the victory will be the more complete &amp; decisive&#8212;&amp; which may eventually ensure a permanent and happy peace
				</para>

				<closing>
					Under those Impressions I have the honor to be Your Most Obt &amp; very Huml Sert
					
					Anty Wayne
				</closing>

				<addressee>
					The Honble
					Major Genl H Knox
					Secretary of War
				</addressee>

			</account>
		</ftAccount>
		<ftAccount>
			<bibInfo>
				<title>Letter from McKee, 27 Aug 1794:</title>
			</bibInfo>
			<account>
				<header>
					Camp Near Fort Miamis, 27th Aug 1794
				</header>
				
				<opening>
					Dear Sir:
				</opening>

				<para>
					It was not possible for me sooner to communicate the events which have lately happened in this country. General Wayne with an Army of Near 4000 men (according to the report of desertion) made gradual approaches towards us until his arrival at Roche de Bout on the 17th Instant where he fixed his head Quarters, on the 18th. The Spy May was taken, who informed the Indians it was intended to attack them the next day. Unless the General should determine to build a Fort, in which case he would not advance until the day following, on the 19th the Indians to the  number of 1300 marched early to the most advantageous ground, but a strong detachment of Cavalry only made their appearance and retired as soon as the Indians showed themselves.
				</para>

				<para>
					On the 20th the American Army advanced and were first attacked by the left of the center of the Indian line which extended near three quarters of a mile obliquely upward. The Americans soon gave way &amp; a rapid pursuit took place for about a mile where the Indian discovered the whole of the American Army Posted to whom they gave Battle retiring slowly before them, during this period, the Wyandot and Ottawas who were on the Right were warmly engaged by the American Left consisting of both Cavalry and infantry who out flanked and infiladed the Indians until they retreated. The whole line of the Indians then retired below the Fort imagining their loss to be much greater then it since appears to have been having seen several of their principal Chiefs fall; the greatest cost they have sustained is in their leaders they settled that night at Swan Creek about five miles below and were not pursued. There were never more than  Indians engaged during the whole day and these stood the shock of a great part of their Army for upward of two hours and lost in the whole but 19 men among whom are to be a  much lamented 8 Principal Chiefs of the Wyandots and two of the Ottawas, besides two more wounded.
				</para>

				<para>
					By the reports of several deserters and from a survey of the field of action (for they did not even bury but few of their dead) it appears the Americans lost between 3 and 400 killed and wounded and a great many horses. The opperations of the Garrison I must leave to be detailed by those whose duty it is, but I must observe to you that all the store houses, my own House with many things that could not be removed were burnt by a Party of General Wayne's Army within sight of the Garrison. I hope soon to have the pleasure of seeing you. At present I am waiting until the Indians whose farmfield and villages are totally destroyed shall determine where they and their families will set themselves down it being on a matter of the highest importance to the interest of Great Britain to prevent if possible their emigrating to the Southern and western points of the Continent they seemingly now having lost all hopes of the Interference of Government.
				</para>

				<para>
					Some letters passed between Major Campbell Commanding Fort Miamis and General Wayne after the action, and on the 22 the American Army quitted the position they had taken within a mile of the Fort and retreated the same way they came but whether on account of the want of Provisions or of an order from Philadelphia cannot be certainly known. The American Army have left evident marks of their boasted Humanity behind them besides scalping and mutilating the Indians who were killed in action they  have opened the peaceful graves in different parts of the Country. Explored the Bones of the consumed &amp; consuming bodies, and horrid to relate they have with unparalleled barbarity driven stakes through them and left them objects calling for more than human vengence.
				</para>

				<closing>
					I am with great regard and esteem
					Dear sir
					Yours very sincerely
					Signed
					AMcKee
				</closing>

				<addressee>
					Joseph Chew Esq
					&amp;c. &amp;c.
					Montreal 20th Sept 1794
				</addressee>
			</account>
		</ftAccount>
		<ftAccount>
			<bibInfo>
				<title>FROM WILLIAM CAMPBELL TO R.G. ENGLAND</title>
			</bibInfo>
			<account>
				<header>
					Fort Miamis, August 20th, 1794.
				</header>

				<opening>
					My Dear Colonel,
				</opening>

				<para>
					I did myself the pleasure to write to you this morning about seven o'clock by Mr. Montigny. Since when we have passed a very odd kind of day. Within less than an hour after he set off a very brisk fire commenced a little higher up than opposite to Colonel McKee's, and increased until near 11 o'clock, when we found a number of Indians coming down upon us in the open, but by far the greatest number of them had been noticed under cover of the wood at some distance in our Front. This fire had for some time no other effect upon our working parties than to frighten our Canadians and it was with a good deal of difficulty we could prevail on them not to run away, but as they said to take to their Arms. However, at last it became so serious that I thought it high time to stand to our Arms, fill up all gaps in our Abatis and shut out all communications from the Fort, by fixing our Chevaux de Frise, &amp;c., &amp;c., not knowing at what moment we might be attacked. The fact was—the Americans and Indians had come to action and the latter were defeated. Some of the Nations fought well but were outgeneralled. The Wyandots, they say, have lost the most, but the loss of men altogether is not great on the part of the Indians. Poor Agushway is shot through the head but not killed. The Little Otter was killed and several other Chiefs. The Americans, they say, have lost a number. Accounts, you may believe, vary. Some make it out as high as 400 but this I do not credit—be that as it may, they seem to have completely gained their point. We see them now feeding their horses upon Colonel McKee's Island, and on this side showing themselves in small bodies very near to us, beating their drums and sounding their horns. Colonel McKee, who has been constantly with the Indians for several days past, called on me as he passed down, and acknowledged they were outgeneraled. The Indians are now totally gone away and I believe towards the Mouth of the River, though he said they were still in spirits and determined to give them another brush. It has been a great relief to my mind that the Battle did not happen so near to this Fort, so as to commit me. You will perceive by this that I still do not expect him to storm our Works. At the same time I shall act in every respect in the safety of the Post as if I did. The only thing I am in difficulty about is to say how far safe it would be for you to send us a reinforcement. If I was to hazard an opinion, I would think it safe and it will give all here great pleasure to see them. As I send this to Colonel McKee to be forwarded to you I hope he may be better able to give you information on this head. In case of any alteration of circumstances, I shall never lose sight of it.
				</para>

				<para>
					I expect this will find Colonel McKee near Point Au Chene&#8212;Would to God the Governor himself were here. Whatever happens I shall do for the best. No one can do more. You shall soon hear from me again. Meantime allow me to subscribe myself.
				</para>

				<closing>
					Ever most faithfully and truly,
				
					Wm. Campbell.
				</closing>

				<postscript>
					P.S.&#8212;Lt. Selbie arrived about three o'clock with your dispatch of the 18th by which I was extremely happy to find all well at Detroit. Captain Harrow and his six sailors are still here. To-morrow morning will probably decide me whether to keep him or not. When we manned our work this morning at Reveille beating, we mustered 160 Rank and File of the 24th, Queen's Rangers, and Artillery, (I beg the Artillery's pardon), exclusive of Canadians and artificers. We have Captain [torn] and about 24 Canadians.
				</postscript>
			</account>
		</ftAccount>
		<ftAccount>
			<bibInfo>
				<title>MAJOR WM. CAMPBELL TO LIEUT. COL. RICHARD ENGLAND.</title>
			</bibInfo>
			<account>
				<header>
					Fort Miamis, 21st August 1794.
				</header>

				<opening>
					Sir,
				</opening>

				<para>
					I sent last night a dispatch to you, to be forwarded by Colonel McKee wherever he should be found, somewhere lower down this River.
				</para>

				<para>
					In it I detailed the Transactions of the day, the chief purpose of which was to inform you, that the Americans &amp; Indians had had an engagement, and the latter were beat, and had retired below this Post, how far I do not know.
				</para>

				<para>
					From the circumstance of an American army having taken Post on the heights opposite to Col. McKees, almost within reach of the Guns of this Fort, and remained there upwards of twenty four hours, without any explanation on their part, I conceived it a duty I owed to my station, &amp; indispensably necessary in support of the honor of the British Colours to desire to be informed upon what Terms they approached so near this Post. I refer you to my letter to Him, now enclosed (and which I hope you will not think unguarded) together with his answer—I sent my Flag by Captain Spears at eleven o'clock this morning—Captain Spears was stopped at their out Post, and was desired to return immediately, as the woods were full of Rifflemen, and they were affraid of his safety, from accident. But that an answer should be sent presently. It arrived at four o'clock. It appears to me, a vain production and still leaves me a cautious part to act. At the same time, if any of his Troops wantonly Insults this Post, it shall not be with Impunity.
				</para>

				<para>
					I sincerely wish the Governor himself may soon arrive, and take all responsibility upon him.
				</para>

				<para>
					I trust a Reinforcement from you is not far off at present, I conceive there is no danger in coming up this River, how long it may be so, is impossible for me to say, at the particular request of Mr Pilkington &amp; Mr. Adye, I keep Capt Harrow and his sailors. I had determined otherwise just now, knowing that you may have great occasion for him, but their entreaties have prevailed.
				</para>

				<para>
					We have not seen or heard a word about a Savage all day. It has been a matter of great comfort to me that the Battle of yesterday terminated without bringing me into a scrape, but surely my situation is a very extraordinary one, hundreds of the American Cavalry are constantly skirting the wood all round us and at this moment, a number of their officers are looking at us from the Point of Colonel McKees Island. You have also enclosed the Information of a Deserter who came in last night. You will observe he mentions Lascell as being taken prisoner, but, here, we all think he Deserted.
				</para>

				<para>
					Drumer Bevan deserted from us this morning about eight o'clock. He went down to the River to wash his Shirts and crept through the Abatis at the water side.
				</para>

				<closing>
					I have the honor to be
					Sir &amp;c. &amp;c.
					
					Wm. Campbell.
				</closing>

				<addressee>
					Lt. Col. England, &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.
				</addressee>
			</account>
		</ftAccount>
		<ftAccount>
			<bibInfo>
				<title>BALTIMORE, September 27. By two gentlemen just arrived from Kentucky we have been favored with the following very Important Intelligence. LEXINGTON, September 8, 1794. An express arrived here on Saturday evening about 8 o'clock with letters from the army, from which we have collected the following particulars:&#8212;</title>
				<pubDate>1794-09-27</pubDate>
				<pubPlace>Baltimore, MD</pubPlace>
				<pubName>Yundt and Patton, near the court-house</pubName>

			</bibInfo>
			<account>
				<para>
					On the 20th ult. about 146 miles advanced
					of Greenville, the advance
					guard, consisting of two companies, were
					attacked by about 1100 Indians and Canadian
					milita; the attack being sudden and
					unexpected, the advance guard fell back on
					the main army and threw them into confusion,
					which occasioned a retreat of about one
					hundred paces before they were ordered to
					charge the enemy, which was instantly done;
					upon which the enemy immediately gave
					ground, and our men rushing forward with
					such impetuosity, the enemy were dislodged
					from their coverts, and the cavalry taking
					advantage of that event, pursued them about
					two miles, when they dispersed. The action
					continued about an hour and a quarter;
					we had about 30 men killed, and 80 wounded;
					among the former are captain Campbell
					of the cavalry, and lieutenant Towles of the
					infantry. Among the latter are captain
					Slough, capt. Vanransallear, capt. Prior and
					lieut. Campbell Smith, of the federal army;&#8212;Seven
					of the Volunteers were killed, and
					fourteen wounded. 127 scalps were taken,
					and a number killed in the river that were
					not scalped. The army remained three days
					on the ground, and returned to Fort-Defiance,
					at the mouth of the Auglaize, where
					they were on the 24th ult.
				</para>
				<para>
					The action happened within sight of a
					strong British fort, regularly built, and garrisoned
					with three hundred men, between
					forty and fifty miles below Fort-Defiance, on
					the Maumee of the Lakes. The commander
					in chief sent a flag to major Campbell, commander
					of the British garrison, to march his
					men out to the nearest British post, and give
					up the fort, both of which he positively refused.
					The Indians had 5000 acres of land
					in corn, all in excellent order on the bottoms
					of the Maumee river, a considerable quantity
					of which the army have destroyed.
				</para>
				<para>
					The following list of the names of the killed and
					wounded of the Kentucky volunteers, was
					received this day.
				</para>
				<para>
					KILLED. John Jackson, Alexander Innes,
					William Mitchell, Thomas Moore, William
					Steel, Benjamin Bell, and James Wiley.
				</para>
				<para>
					WOUNDED. Captain Rawlings, lieutenant
					M'Kinney, ensign Duncan. Privates, George
					M'Cullock, John Howard, Robert
					Scott, John Hinkston, Isaac Rankins, James
					Cost, James Stewart, Benjamin Bantle, John
					Montgomery, and William Woodrow.
				</para>
				<closing>
					BALTIMORE: Printed by Yundt and Patton, near the Court-House.
				</closing>
			</account>
		</ftAccount>
	</ftAccounts>