<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../xslt/ftaccounts.xsl"?>

<ftAccounts xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../ftAccounts.xsd">
  <ftAccount id="05">
    <bibInfo medium="journal" distance="primary" format="book" text="edited_reprint">
      <pubTitle>
        From Greene Ville to Fallen Timbers, A Journal of the Wayne Campaign: July 28-September 14, 1794
      </pubTitle>
      <pubAuthor>
        Anonymous [James Wilkinson]
      </pubAuthor>
      <pubEditor>
        Dwight L. Smith
      </pubEditor>
      <pubName>
        Indiana Historical Society
      </pubName>
      <pubPlace city="Indianapolis" state="Indiana"></pubPlace>
      <pubDate date="1952">
        1952
      </pubDate>
      <pubPage>
        288-
      </pubPage>
    </bibInfo>
    <account>
      <header>
        August 20th 1794&#8212;
      </header>
      <para>
        marched this morning about 7 O'Clk
        instead of the hour prescribed&#8212;the troops divested of every
        species of baggage except their blankets&#8212;the strength of the
        right Column was precisely 368 non commissioned-officers
        and privates&#8212;say of the 3 S Legn 250 and of the 1st S L. 118.
        the C in C ordered that the files should be doubled, and an
        interval of at least 200 yards from the centre column to be
        observed&#8212;<person>Capt Springer</person> who led the right flank Rifle Men
        was ordered to observe an equal distance from the Column&#8212;<person>the
        old Man</person> has forgot the Columns of Cavalry and light
        Infantry which must be between the main right Column and the
        Riflemen&#8212;the regulation gives the right wing a front of 800
        yards&#8212;this however is a pardonable&#8212;but his total deviation
        from the promise made yesterday to <person>Genl W.</person> to alter his disposition
        of march, is in every view unpardonable&#8212;now if we
        had an enemy of military sagacity to contend with, he might
        with facility turn either our right or left flank, neither of which
        I am well assured have been examined more than two or three
        miles, and when we reach the extent of our march fall suddenly
        upon our baggage and provision, and by destroying them not
        only defeat the expedition but actually destroy the army, as we
        take but two days provision with us&#8212;the face of the Country
        as we leave our encampment is agreable&#8212;the day hot and
        clear&#8212;the river bubbling over a Rocky sheet is bordered by a
        luxuriant prairie from 1/4 of a mile to 600 yards wide&#8212;then
        we have a regular swell rising to the height of 80 or 100 feet
        covered with timber of various denominations which is sparse
        on the brow of this height, runing almost paralel with the
        River but inclining to the left&#8212;the surface is flat&#8212;the wood
        thickens&#8212;becomes swampy and in some places almost impervious
        from the underwood and small growth&#8212;it may be
        necessary to add that the high ground before spoken of which
        flanks the river in a direction nearly paralel,&#8212;is cut by many
        deep, steep and short ravines, runing nearly at right angles to
        the general course of this height&#8212;
      </para>
      <para>
        having advanced about 4 miles I rode to the brow of this
        height with <person>Genl W.</person> who wanted to examine the position of his
        flank column and to get a view of <person>McKee</person>s house on the East
        side of the river, and of the British Post with the flag flying
        below&#8212;<person>Genl W</person> made report of this to the <person>C in C</person> in the centre
        whose <person>aid de Camp Capt De B</person> and <person>Mr E. the Contractor</person>
        returned with him to take a view of the fort&#8212;when we reached
        the brow of the height, our attention was called by <person>Dr Heyward</person>
        to some horsemen who were pushing rapidly across the
        prairie about 1/4 of a mile in our front&#8212;it was first supposed
        they were a part of the volunteers in quest of plunder but observing
        them to alter their direction for our front and hearing
        at the same moment a few shot&#8212;<person>Genl W</person> rode up to <person>Capt
        De B</person> and requested him to hasten to the <person>C in C</person> and apprize
        him that our advance was attacked and retreating&#8212;he had
        scarcly made this observation when 40 or 50 of the mounted
        volunteers were discovered to be retreating directly toward us,
        in great confusion and before a faint fire of the enemy&#8212;the
        moment was critical as the troops had not yet received orders
        to form&#8212;<person>Genl W.</person> hailed and halted the retreating party&#8212;reminded
        them of their name fame &amp; Country and exhorted
        them to turn and oppose the Enemy who were runing forward
        and throwing their shot at random and were by this within
        150 yards&#8212;several agreed to try and fight&#8212;but <person>the General</person>s
        presence being necessarily called to the command of his wing&#8212;the
        moment his back was turned they broke and resumed their
        flight thro the 1st Sub Legion then forming&#8212;
      </para>
      <para>
        <person>the Genl</person> having brought up <person>Gaine</person>s' Light Infantry and
        formed them in advance to check the enemy, repaired immediately
        to his left which was pressed by the Enemy&#8212;they were
        almost formed, tho in order, much too close&#8212;this defect
        was soon remedied and the troops stood with shouldered arms&#8212;when
        we reached the extreme left of the 3d S Legn we found
        <person>Capt Miss Campbell</person>, retreating with his troop in good Order&#8212;and
        also that <person>Capt H Lewis</person> who commanded the advanced
        light Infantry &amp; Rifle Men had fallen back and was mixed
        with the left of the right wing&#8212;we were at this time under a
        scattered fire of the Enemy at 100 yards distance&#8212;<person>Genl W</person>
        enquired of <person>Capt Miss Campbell</person> "what was the matter in front"
        he answered "every thing is confusion" and asked <person>the Genl</person>
        what he should do, who observed to him, that he not being
        under his command he could give him no orders, but recommended
        to him to fall back &amp; form squadron in his rear&#8212;<person>the
        Genl</person> then pushed towards the right, when we gained the right
        of the 3d S. L. then commanded by <person>Cap Kingsbury</person>, found
        the Enemy within 80 yards, <person>Mr Gaines</person> in the interim having
        changed his position by order from <person>some person unknown</person> and
        firing as warmly as the smallness of their number would permit&#8212;<person>Kingsbury</person>
        applied to <person>the General</person> for permission to
        charge but he having no orders or authority for that purpose
        forbid him &amp; commanded him to stand his ground--he then
        ordered <person>a Serjeant of Dragoons</person> (neither of aids being near to
        him) to ride to <person>Capt Springer</person> &amp; inform him it was his desire
        that he should push forward and flank the Enemy on their
        left&#8212;returning to the centre <person>Kingsbury</person> again asked leave to
        charge, which was refused, as no order had been received or
        signal heard to that effect&#8212;at this instant <person>Miss Campbell</person>
        ordered the charge and dashing forward, passed the 1st Battn
        of the 3d S L. before <person>the Genl</person> could speak to him; in making
        this charge he was obliged to cross a steep ravine in our rear
        and to ascend a narrow point across which the troops of the
        right were formed&#8212;the ground in front was open and smooth
        and the Enemy at 80 or 100 yards distance&#8212;<person>Genl W</person> seeing
        the peril to which this movement exposed <person>Miss Campbell</person>,
        instantly (and without orders) directed a general charge&#8212;but
        being immediately informed that the height and strength of the
        grass in the prairie prevented the Riflemen from getting forward
        he sent his <person>A D. C. Capt Shaumburgh</person> to <person>Capt Springer</person>
        with directions to bring him into action on the high ground&#8212;and
        as the light Infantry under <person>Gaines</person> were similarly circumstanced,
        he presumed tho without authority to give similar
        orders to him&#8212;he also ventured to form <person>Lieut. Webb</person> with the
        first troop in his rear, with orders to follow the line at 150 yards
        distance&#8212;
      </para>
      <para>
        the charge succeeded as directed, the enemy making little
        or no resistance, but fell back from ravine to ravine loading &amp;
        firing at a considerable distance as we advanced&#8212;the fire was
        truly so light and the resistance so feeble, that we began to apprehend
        a deception and that the enemy had sent forward light
        parties to harrass and disorder us, and to draw us in that Condition
        into the hands of their main body&#8212;under this impression
        <person>Genl W</person> rode to the <person>C in C</person> whom he found in the centre and
        suggested to him his apprehensions and the propriety of halting
        and forming&#8212;he told him, to do so&#8212;but the intention was
        defeated by an increased fire from the enemy on the left&#8212;the
        charge was therefore renewed after a momentary and partial
        halt which had not given time to form the line&#8212;during the
        pause <person>the Genl</person> sent his extra <person>aid de Camp, Lieut C. Smith</person>
        with a message to the <person>C in C</person>&#8212;he sought but could not find him
        and returning received a shot in his right breast which by the
        faculty is deemed to be mortal&#8212;this affair had lasted nearly an
        hour&#8212;the artillery were left behind, the light Infantry and
        Rifle Men could not get up into the action and the troops were
        much disordered&#8212;the charge still continued &amp; the fire of the
        enemy began to slacken&#8212;At this moment <person>Lieut Covington</person>
        of the Dragoons was observed in our front charging from the
        left to our right with 6 or 8 Dragoons, and the ground being
        even and the wood open, having gained our right near the brow
        of the height he wheeled to the left and was charging to the
        front, the enemy being then in view and retreating&#8212;<person>Genl W</person>
        sent his <person>A. D. C. Mr Shamburgh</person> to order <person>Lieut Webb</person> to
        charge&#8212;and called to <person>Covington</person> to halt, but as his voice could
        not reach him and seeing him rushing upon destruction&#8212;(as
        he would with 6 or 8 men have been in with the Enemy long
        before <person>Webb</person> could get up) in order to save him, he determined
        to make a decisive tho not very justifiable attempt&#8212;he clapped
        spurs to his horse &amp; runing at full speed about 250 yards in
        front of his line and close upon the rear of the Enemy, passed
        and halted <person>Covington</person> for a moment&#8212;this gave time for <person>Webb</person>
        to shew himself and support&#8212;in making this movement <person>the
        Genl</person> had thrown himself between <person>Covington</person> and <person>a Savage</person>
        who presented his piece at him but did not fire, altho' he passed
        within a few paces of him&#8212;<person>Covington</person> seeing his danger,
        charged this son of the woods, sword in hand and killed him
        on the spot&#8212;<person>the Genl</person> having accomplished his purpose which
        was to save or to give a fair chance to a gallant officer and an
        amiable man, wheeled and rejoined his command which was
        still advancing--mean time <person>Covington</person> &amp; <person>Webb</person> kept up the
        charge and we saw no more of the Enemy&#8212;<person>Covington</person> killed
        two and <person>Webb</person> <person>one Indian</person> with their own hands&#8212;the retreat
        soon after beat, when we halted and formed in one line&#8212;
      </para>
      <para>
        in the commencement of the action <person>Capt Shamburgh</person>
        (whom <person>the Genl</person> had left at the head of his Column to receive
        orders for him while he road to the right) having heard a
        firing in front, rode to the centre and apprised the <person>C in C</person> of our
        being attacked&#8212;who replyed, "Yes, I heard it, there was 6 or
        8 Guns"&#8212;the other rejoined in surprise "6 or 8 Sir! I have
        heard at least 150 shot" and turned off in disgust&#8212;at this
        instant the Militia were discovered to be flying in front&#8212;		some
        person near the <person>C in C</person> then observed that they were
        runing and asked what was to be done after a short pause&#8212;the
        <person>C. in C.</person> bawled out "prepare to receive the Enemy in front in
        two Lines"&#8212;but his voice could not be heard 150 yards at
        which distance each Column was from the centre and this was
        the only order we received from him prior to or during the
        action&#8212;<person>Col. H</person> informs also, that he received no order during
        the action, or for forming&#8212;<person>Genl W</person> formed in one line&#8212;he in
        two&#8212;consequently the 2d S L. scarcely got into the action and
        the 4th S L was at one period nearly out flanked&#8212;the light
        Infantry &amp; Dragoons who were selected and reserved for the <person>C
        in C</person>'s special command, acted I am well assured, without orders
        from him&#8212;notwithstanding the wise precaution which have
        been taken by frittering up the army, into guards &amp; Detachments,
        we were fairly surprised, &amp; the Enemy within Gun-Shot
        of us before we were formed&#8212;it is unquestionable with me,
        that if the Enemy had struck with their whole force at any
        point of our army&#8212;instead of attempting with 900 men to
        form a line of two miles they would have penetrated and if they
        pleased passed thro us, making great havock at least&#8212;all the
        pompous and prolix orders of battle, heretofore issued and received,
        were here entirely neglected, not a word was uttered
        about forming the square&#8212;the light Infantry, Rifle Men &amp;
        Cavalry attacked immediately&#8212;fell back to the Columns and
        were not fixed upon total extirpation&#8212;neither of these Corps
        were embodied and they were in general left to exercise their
        own discretion&#8212;yet when I saw the <person>C in C</person> he appeared tranquil&#8212;no
        attempt was made to profit by our victory&#8212;altho'
        very few of the volunteers had been engaged&#8212;and a great
        proportion of our Dragoons were in vigorous plight&#8212;instead
        of letting loose 1700 men upon the disordered rear of the
        dismayed fugitives, we made a dead halt the moment the fire
        of the enemy ceased and they were not pursued one single step,
        except by the Dragoons under <person>Covington</person> and <person>Webb</person>&#8212;the
        Command of whom <person>Genl W.</person> had assumed&#8212;this looks more
        like unto a drawn battle than a victory&#8212;if <person>Miss Campbell</person>
        charged by order, he was sacrificed&#8212;if of his own accord he
        threw away his life&#8212;his loss is to be regretted as he was a
        good officer&#8212;
      </para>
      <para>
        this affair which does not deserve the name of a Battle
        began at 10 O Clk and the troops halted at 5 minutes after 11
        O'Clk&#8212;we remained on the ground untill 4 O'Clk&#8212;no order
        was given by the <person>C in C</person> to collect and bury the dead or to
        recover the axes and mens blanketts, which had been dropt in
        the begining of the fight&#8212;Individuals sought for their
        wounded friends&#8212;and <person>Genl W.</person> without order, made a small
        detachment for this purpose&#8212;these when collected were
        ordered back to deposit Camp under the Escort of a Body of
        volunteers and the army moved forward at O'Clk to
        encamp on the Bank of the Miami in sight of and about one
        mile distant from the British fort&#8212;several of the wounded
        who were left with the volunteers, were brought back into
        Camp after dark, &amp; about 8 O'Clk this evening <person>Genl Todd</person>
        brought in a wounded man who had been found on the field by
        the militia&#8212;the <person>C in C</person> seems disposed to confer the honor
        of the day upon the left Wing or rather 4th Sub Legion&#8212;a
        small number only of the volunteers got into the action on the
        left and behaved well&#8212;a partial and impolitic issue of whiskey
        was made after the affair was over, of which the volunteers
        were excluded from partaking&#8212;the <person>C in C</person> this evening swore
        that "he had seen in front of the 4th S Legn at one view, 400
        Savages as naked by by the eternal God! as they came out
        of their mothers Wombs"&#8212;<person>a french man</person>, painted and dressed,
        as a Savage, was found after the affair terminated, conceal near
        the river bank armed with a double barrelled fusee&#8212;he is
        recognised by <person>Col. Hamtramck</person> as a former resident of Ouittanon&#8212;he
        says he is a trader&#8212;that he arrived at the British
        Fort, the evening before&#8212;that his boat had been taken to bring
        up provision from Cedar Island and that he had been forced
        to go into the Battle tho' he had not fired his gun&#8212;which from
        examination appeared to be true&#8212;he informs that the Body
        opposed to us consisted of 900 Indians about 40 White men&#8212;that
        the Indians were averse to the action but that <person>Elliot</person> &amp;
        <person>McKee</person> who were engaged in person dragged them into it
        telling them, they need but make a trial of what they could
        do&#8212;he says the Women &amp; children had been removed a considerable
        distance below the fort and that he expects the Indians
        will draw off and wait the issue of an attack upon that place&#8212;he
        adds that messages had been sent to all the nations to
        assemble&#8212;that the Chippiways had refused to come and he
        did not know what might be the determination of the other
        Nations&#8212;he further says that an express had been sent to
        Niagara for a reinforcement to the Garrison&#8212;that he whole
        force of the British Garrison is 250 and that 50 of these are
        sick&#8212;It is worthy of remark here that this evening after the
        army halted, the <person>C in C</person> got into a violent passion with <person>Capt
        Ford</person>, whose men warm with fatigue &amp; nearly exhausted had
        pulled off their Coats&#8212;in the course of his ravings, he addressed
        himself to a drummer who happened to be present and
        said&#8212;"I have fought under the hotest and the coldest suns
        and such a thing never was permitted nor shall it now be done&#8212;it
        is damned cowardly"&#8212;
      </para>
      <para>
        Without disparagement to any person the Individual act of
        greatest Gallantry this day exhibited on the right, was performed
        by <person>Lieut. Shamburgh A D C</person> to <person>Brg Genl Wilkinson</person>&#8212;this
        officer being sent by his Genl with an order to the light
        troops of the right flank&#8212;and perceiving as he led on part of
        the light Infantry under <person>Ensign Claiborne</person>, a party of savages
        firing from a Covert of Bushes and high grass on the Margin
        of the Prairie&#8212;he, sword in hand dashed into the thickett,
        gained the rear of <person>an Indian warrior</person> and the pursuit actually
        actually forced him upon the bayonets of <person>Claiborne</person>'s
        party&#8212;
      </para>
      <para>
        It is also a tribute due to <person>Mr R Elliot</person> the Contractor to
        declare&#8212;that he so far participated in the action, as to lead two
        companies of the Kentucky volunteers, who were lost and
        flying, up to the fire of the enemy&#8212;an office which few
        men in his Station would have undertaken.
      </para>
    </account>
    </ftAccount>
</ftAccounts>