<?xml version="1.0"?>
  <ftAccount id="11">
    <bibInfo medium="narrative" distance="primary" text="edited_reprint">
      <pubTitle>
        A Sketch of the Early Adventures of William Sudduth in Kentucky
      </pubTitle>
      <pubAuthor persID="">
        William Sudduth
      </pubAuthor>
      <pubEditor persID="">
        Lucien Beckner
      </pubEditor>
      <pubName>
        The History Quarterly
      </pubName>
      <pubVol>
        2
      </pubVol>
      <pubIss>
        2
      </pubIss>
      <pubDate date="1928">
        1928
      </pubDate>
      <pubPage>

      </pubPage>
    </bibInfo>
    <account>
      <para>
        ...The next morning Orders were for
        the detachment of Spies to march by sun rise but we were
        prevented by a thunderstorm coming on. It cleared off about
        Eight oclock and we proceeded on untill we came within
        about half a mile of where the Indians had caused us to retreat
        the day before.
      </para>
      <para>
        The detachment got water &amp; stript off all unnecessary
        clothing. It was usual with us to guard against surprise, to
        keep two men in front of each line about one hundred yards.
        We generally called them out in rotation as they stood on the
        list. I observed to the men not to dispute about who was next
        on duty that this was the day to gain honor and nearly half
        my line turned out. I recalled them all except two Thomas
        Moore &amp; William Steele. They moved on briskley &amp; had not
        advanced more than one hundred yards untill they fell into an
        ambuscade and were both shot down. We advanced briskley
        untill we came within twenty yards of the Indians &amp; received
        their full fire. Moore was not dead &amp; was taken up &amp; put on a
        horse untill he died. Maj. Price then Ordered a retreat &amp; lead
        it about sixty steps. The course we took lead us along the
        head of the Indian line &amp; they fired on us with a tremendious
        roar at a verry short distance. We passed that body of Indians
        &amp; saw another party advancing upon us headed by several
        horsemen, Maj. Price then Ordered us to halt &amp; fight them. At
        that instant some of the Indian horsemen fired upon us at about
        forty steps distance. Maj Price then returned their fire which
        caused them to pause. I then fired at one of the horsemen who
        instantly fell from his horse. Lucas Hood &amp; Harry Martin were
        one on each side of me with their guns cocked &amp; up to their faces
        to shoot, but he fell so quick as to save their fire. We then
        received a verry heavy fire from the foot men. The Maj.
        then Ordered a retreat to the main army which was briskly
        advancing to support us.
      </para>
      <para>
        We had retreated some distance when a man called out to
        me by name that we were leaving a wounded man. I looked
        back &amp; saw the man running after us &amp; the Indians in full persuit
        after him. They were about seventy yards behind us &amp; the
        wounded man about half way between the two lines. I immediately
        stoped my horse &amp; called to the men who would go
        back with me. Maj. Price was close by me; he neither said
        go or stay. I turned back &amp; five men went with me. When we
        met the wounded man the Indians were from thirty to thirty
        five steps from him. They immediately droped in the weeds
        &amp; bushes &amp; commenced a heavy fire on us. I turned my horse
        round and the wounded man tried twice to jump behind me &amp;
        failed. I then turned the side of my horse to him &amp; put out
        my foot for him to get up in that manner in which he failed also.
        William Richie from Mason &amp; Harvey Martin from Clarke lit
        from their horses &amp; lifted the man up behind me during which
        time the Indians kept up an incessant fire at us at about thirty
        or thirty five steps distance. I could see into the muzel of many
        of their guns when they raised them to fire on us. The bark of
        the trees flew into our faces just as they had put the man up
        behind me &amp; the man to my right hand he sliped off, the Indians
        shot my horse. The ball passed between the thy of the man
        behind me &amp; my own &amp; cut the hind part of the pad of my sadle.
        The men that were with me then left me and the horse became
        unmanageable; he reared up three times &amp; would not move out
        of the place. The Indians by this time advanced with their
        tomahawks drawn verry close to me and I believe if my horse
        had have seen the Indian horses he would have run to them but
        fortunately he discovered the horses of the men that had left
        me and followed them. I gave him the spur &amp; pushed him on
        the blood gushing out of the wound, his mouth &amp; nose verry fast.
        He ran about one hundred and fifty yards &amp; stoped. I leaped
        off him &amp; left the man, who informed me afterwards that the
        horse fell immediately after I left him. We had got far anough
        in advance of the Indians for the wounded man to save himself.
      </para>
      <para>
        When I left the horse I ran on after my party &amp; they halted
        for me. I got up behind one of them and soon met the front of
        the Army coming up to our support. I then loaded my gun.
        A man by the name of White dismounted &amp; gave me up his horse.
        He had heard me receive orders that morning to endeavor to
        turn the right flank of the Indians &amp; said I could not perform
        the service on foot. I immediately mounted the horse &amp; returned
        towards the front of the Indians. I collected about
        thirty or thirty five of the Spies, part belonging to each company.
        I shaped my course course in front of the Indian line &amp;
        passed between them &amp; our Army, as they approached each other,
        untill they came so close to each other that a Company of
        regulars on our extreme right had to open to the right &amp; left to
        let us pass. As we passed the fire of both Armies closed after
        us; the Indians were passing on endeavoring to turn our right
        wing. I continued in the same direction within gunshot of them
        and several times halted to fire on them but they continued to
        try to out flank us. I at last pushed on untill I passed their left
        &amp; wheeled around their extreme point of their left wing. They
        then raised a schrill hallow which was answered in the same
        manner back along their line that ended the battle in less than
        two minutes. The firing ceased &amp; the Indians retreated. It is
        stated by some that the Indians were persued but it was not the
        case.
      </para>
      <para>
        The army remained some time on the battle ground and then
        encamped near the British garrison of about three hundred men
        commanded by Maj. Campbell. That evening &amp; the following
        two days the men destroyed the corn that stood near the garrison,
        burnt their hay, &amp; gardens, &amp; every out house, among
        otherst the house of Col. MeKee, an Indian trader. The next
        day after the battle the spies were sent down the river about seven
        miles on the direction the Indians had retreated. In many
        places for several yards in weadth they had tread down the
        weeds like a log had been roled over it. We discovered no
        Indians &amp; returned to Camp. Our loss in battle was about one
        hundred in killed &amp; wounded. We had five killed in our Company,
        but none wounded that survived the first night. It was
        reported that the Americans got forty two scalps. It was supposed
        from appearances that many more were killed &amp; taken off
        or threw into a pond near where we fought....
      </para>
    </account>
  </ftAccount>